<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../PublishingDTD/source_DTDs/journalpublishing.dtd">
<article>
<front>
<?mtl hellip?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id
journal-id-type="pubmed">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id
journal-id-type="publisher">PNAS</journal-id><issn>0027-8424</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The
National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id
pub-id-type="publisher-id">4214</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677462</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group><subj-group>
<subject>Special
Feature</subject></subj-group><series-title>Perspective</series-title><series-title>Special
Feature</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Was a change in thermohaline
circulation responsible for the Little Ice
Age?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>Wallace
S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes"
rid="FN151">&#x2020;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Lamont-Doherty Earth
Observatory of Columbia University, Palisades, NY 10964</aff><author-notes><fn
id="FN151"><p>To whom reprint requests should be addressed.
E-mail: <email>broecker@ldeo.columbia.edu</email>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date
pub-type="pub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>
97</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1342</lpage><copyright-statement>
Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, The National Academy of
Sciences</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
</article-meta>
<?mtl /hellip?></front>
<body><?mtl hellip?><p>Long-term (&#x2248;800-year) and short-term (&#x2248;20-year)
estimates of the rate of deep water formation in the Southern Ocean are in
serious disagreement. This disagreement suggests to me that the rate of deep
water formation may have been larger during the Little Ice Age (LIA) than it is
now.</p><p>Based on studies of ice-rafted debris in northern Atlantic sediments,
a strong case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) has been made that a
cycle averaging about 1,500 years in duration punctuated the climate in this
region both during the Holocene and during the last interglacial period. This
finding reinforces the earlier suggestion of a 2,000-year cycle (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) based on CaCO<sub>3</sub> measurements in a
high accumulation rate core raised off Bermuda. Because the frequency of these
cycles is about the same as that for the much larger (and hence more famous)
Dansgaard&#x2013;Oeschger cycles of glacial time, the possibility has been
raised (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) that both the glacial and the
interglacial cycles share a common causal factor. Because a considerable amount
of circumstantial evidence suggests that the Dansgaard&#x2013;Oeschger cycles
are linked to a seesawing of deep water formation between the Northern Atlantic
and the Southern Ocean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), it has been suggested further (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) that perhaps the weaker interglacial cycles
may also be driven by alternations in the mode of deep water formation. In
addition, the LIA, well recorded in the region around the Northern Atlantic, was
the most recent of this series of cold pulses (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B1">1</xref>). An extension of this logic would then suggest that a change
in thermohaline circulation accompanied the LIA.</p><p>Before providing evidence
that indeed such a change may well have occurred, it is appropriate to review
what is known about the magnitude and global distribution of the impact of the
LIA. The most reliable source of information comes from reconstructions of the
elevations of mountain snowlines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).
Herein, I focus on the last gasp of the LIA, that is, the mid to late 1800s. The
reason is that the records are reasonably complete for its final
phase&#x2014;unlike the record for earlier LIA phases, which are quite spotty.
Trees that grew on abandoned LIA moraines record the time of the onset of the
retreat, which marked the end of this 500-year cold snap.</p><p>Also, by the
late 1800s, geologists and geographers had reached even the most remote parts of
the world and mapped the extent of mountain glaciers (see Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> for an example). The bottom line is that, in
both the north and the south temperate zones of our planet, snowlines (that is,
the boundaries separating zones of net accumulation from those of net ablation)
were about 100 m lower than they were in 1975. This difference is comparable to
a snowline lowering of 900 to 950 m during full glacial time and to a roughly
350-m lowering during the Younger Dryas (Y.D.). Because the major factor
influencing these elevations is air temperature, the suggestion is that, during
all three of these cold intervals, the cooling was symmetrical about the
equator. Based on present-day lapse rates, the mountain cooling during glacial
time was about 5.5&#x00B0;C and that during the LIA was about 0.6&#x00B0;C.
</p><fig id="F1"><caption><p>Historic climate records
extending back to A.D. 1600. (<italic>Upper</italic>) A record of the number of months
per year sea ice was present around Iceland and its relationship to mean annual
temperature available since A.D. 1850 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>).
(<italic>Lower</italic>) The extent of the front of the Grindelwald Glacier as
reconstructed from oil paintings, drawings, prints, photos, maps, and literature
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>).</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0204214001"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>In addition to the snowline record, there is
historical evidence, which extends back to about A.D. 1600, that the Northern
Atlantic had greater ice cover during the LIA. This record (Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) shows that from 1650 to 1890 Iceland was
surrounded by sea ice for an average of 2 months per year. During the present
century, a dramatic decrease in sea ice occurred. By 1920, the waters around
Iceland were free of sea ice for the entire year. Of course, the finding (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) that the deposition of ice-rafted debris in
the region west of Iceland was greater during the LIA is consistent with these
historic records.</p><p>Clearly then, the LIA, although much smaller in
amplitude, shared the geographic pattern of Y.D. and the main glacial maximum.
However, the big question is whether this agreement extends to an antiphased
warming in the Antarctic region. This idea is key to the bipolar seesaw (see
<xref ref-type="app">Appendix</xref>). There is only one piece of evidence I
know of that bears on this question. A deconvolution of the down hole
temperature record at the Taylor Dome Antarctica ice-core site has been
conducted (G. Clow, personal communication). Preliminary results suggest that
during the LIA the air temperature warmed by 3&#x00B0;C. Although, admittedly,
the Taylor Dome <sup>18</sup>O record for the deglacial interval is anomalous
compared with that for the other Antarctic ice cores (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B8">8</xref>), this result is tantalizing and certainly points to the
importance of obtaining high quality thermal records at other Antarctic ice-core
sites. If these temperature reconstructions were to be confirmed, the LIA
warming in Antarctica would certainly be the smoking gun with regard to the
involvement of thermohaline circulation.</p><p>Even so, this evidence is, by its
very nature, circumstantial. Is there any more direct evidence that suggests
that thermohaline circulation during the last century differs substantially from
that during the LIA? The answer to this question is yes; there is evidence
regarding the nature of this circulation for two quite different time scales
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B12">12</xref>). As the renewal time of the deep Pacific and Indian Oceans
is on the order of 800 years, the properties of these waters integrate from
times before the LIA all the way to the present. By contrast, the distribution
of anthropogenic tracers such as chlorofluorocarbon-11 (CFC-11) constrain the
magnitude of the production of deep water over the last 2 decades. As is
outlined below, when taken together, these two sets of data strongly suggest
that the rate of formation of ventilated deep water in the Southern Ocean has
been several times lower during the &#x201C;Freon era&#x201D; (i.e., the last
few decades) than on the average over the last ocean-mixing cycle.</p><p>First,
I will consider the long-term situation. In almost all studies of thermohaline
circulation, the properties of the deep sea are taken to represent a
steady-state circulation. To test whether this assumption is fair, the
distributions of three properties in the deep sea have been analyzed,
specifically, the concentrations of dissolved oxygen, the concentration of
dissolved phosphate, and the <sup>14</sup>C/C in dissolved inorganic carbon
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). By combining the PO<sub>4</sub> and
O<sub>2</sub> results, a quasiconservative property, PO<sub>4</sub>*, is
obtained. PO<sub>4</sub>* allows the assessment of the fraction of the water in
the deep Pacific and Indian Oceans that originated in the Northern Atlantic and
the fraction that originated in the Southern Ocean (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B9">9</xref>). PO<sub>4</sub>* is calculated as follows: PO<sub>4</sub>* =
PO<sub>4</sub> &#x002B; O<sub>2</sub>/175 &#x2212; 1.95 &#x03BC;mol/kg, where
175 is the global ocean ratio of O<sub>2</sub> consumed to PO<sub>4</sub>
released during respiration and 1.95 is an arbitrary constant. Although the deep
waters generated in both of these source regions have O<sub>2</sub> contents on
the order of 310 &#x03BC;mol/kg, they differ greatly in PO<sub>4</sub> content.
Those in the Northern Atlantic average &#x2248;0.9 &#x03BC;mol/kg, and those
adjacent to the margin of the Antarctic continent average &#x2248;2.1
&#x03BC;mol/kg. The resulting PO<sub>4</sub>* values are 0.73 &#x00B1; 0.04 for
new deep waters formed in the North and 1.95 &#x00B1; 0.05 for deep waters
formed in the Southern Ocean. The PO<sub>4</sub>* values for the waters north of
40&#x00B0;S and deeper than 1,500 m in the Pacific and Indian Ocean are quite
uniform and cluster in a narrow range around an average of 1.38 &#x03BC;mol/kg
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). This uniformity suggests that they
are a mixture consisting of 53&#x0025; southern source water and 47&#x0025;
northern source water. As both of these source waters flow into the rapidly
circulating circum-Antarctic ring current, they become well mixed before moving
northward into the deep Pacific and Indian Oceans. Thus, the above inventory
ratio should reflect the production ratio of these two water types.</p><p>The
ratio of <sup>14</sup>C to C in the dissolved inorganic carbon allows the actual
production rate of these two end members to be constrained. I have (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) analyzed the radiocarbon budget in a number
of ways. All are consistent with a total production rate of 30 &#x00B1; 6
Sverdrups (that is, 10<sup>6</sup> m<sup>3</sup>/s) or roughly 15 Sverdrups in
each of the two source regions.</p><p>An inversion scheme has been developed
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) that is designed to match
simultaneously four properties of the deep sea water (potential temperature,
salinity, PO<sub>4</sub>*, and <sup>14</sup>C/C). The conclusions of this study
are consistent with the above; namely, nearly equal amounts of ventilated deep
water must be produced in the two major source regions, and the total production
must be on the order of 30 Sverdrups.</p><p>However, a problem emerged. Studies
conducted in the Weddell Sea&#x2014;to which physical oceanographers looked as
the main site for deep water production in the Southern Ocean&#x2014;all reached
similar conclusions, that is, that the total production of ventilated deep water
was on the order of 2&#x2013;5 Sverdrups (see ref. <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B3">3</xref> for a summary of this evidence). In ref. <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B3">3</xref>, I leaned toward the explanation that major amounts of deep
water must be forming at other sites around the margin of the Antarctic
continent. Analysis of the then-available CFC-11 results (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B3">3</xref>), to see whether the deep Southern Ocean inventory supported
the multiple source hypothesis, yielded results that were ambiguous (aerial
coverage of CFC-11 measurements was not adequate at that time).</p><p>Based on
the results from the World Ocean Circulation Experiment survey in the Southern
Ocean, a complete inventory of the amount of CFC-11 in the dense bottom waters
in the Southern Ocean has been compiled (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B12">12</xref>). If it is assumed, as both O<sub>2</sub> and CFC
measurements suggest, that the newly ventilated waters achieve
&#x2248;75&#x0025; saturation with atmospheric gases (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F2">2</xref>), then the inventory in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B12">12</xref> translates to an average of only 4 Sverdrups of Southern
Ocean deep water formation during the last 2 decades. If this result stands the
test of time, then clearly the formation rate of ventilated deep water in the
Southern Ocean is currently several times smaller than its average for the last
deep ocean-mixing cycle (that is, &#x2248;800 years).</p><fig
id="F2"><caption><p>Plot of CFC-11 concentration as a
function of PO<sub>4</sub>* for waters south of 40&#x00B0;S from depths less
than 500 m and with temperatures less than 3&#x00B0;C. As can be seen, many of
the points scatter around a mixing line joining the compositions of CFC-11 free
water with a PO<sub>4</sub>* value of 1.38 &#x03BC;mol/kg (characteristic of
upwelling circumpolar deep water) and water with a PO<sub>4</sub>* value of 1.95
&#x03BC;mol/kg (characteristic of newly forming deep water). As can be seen,
this water is about 75&#x0025; saturated with CFC-11.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0204214002"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>At this point, one might ask whether the
CFC-11 inventory of Northern Atlantic waters is consistent with a ventilation
rate of 15 Sverdrups during the last 2 decades. Such an inventory has been
generated (W. Smethie, personal communication) and reveals that the new deep
water is forming somewhat more slowly than expected. However, because CFC-11 has
spread over a very large portion of the North Atlantic, the existing surveys do
not provide enough coverage to allow a firm answer to be given.</p><p>Although
the evidence in hand is surely consistent with a reduction in deep water
formation during the LIA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), clearly
other explanations must be considered. For example, perhaps deep water
production in the Southern Ocean is episodic on a multidecadal time scale, and
no such episode has occurred during the period when observations are available.
Or perhaps global warming has already taken its toll on deep water formation in
the Southern Ocean. Although I favor the LIA explanation, this early in the
game, there is no way to rule out others.</p><fig id="F3"><caption><p>Ventilation rate scenario designed to account for both the
global distribution of PO<sub>4</sub>* and <sup>14</sup>C and for the current
inventories of CFCs in the deep Northern Atlantic Ocean and the deep Southern
Ocean. The units are Sverdrups (i.e., 10<sup>6</sup>
m<sup>3</sup>/s).</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0204214003"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>Perhaps the greatest weakness in the LIA
explanation is the failure of the patterns of distribution of properties in the
deep sea to provide a hint that a change has occurred. It is generally accepted
that the distributions of temperature, salinity, nutrient constituents, and
radiocarbon are interpreted as reflecting a steady state. There seems to be no
evidence for a reduction of the PO<sub>4</sub>* value in Southern Ocean deep
water, which should be developing if the inflow of new high-PO<sub>4</sub>*
water has been reduced during the last 100 years (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B13">13</xref>). Further, only recently have studies of sediments with high
enough sedimentation rates to preserve evidence for LIA changes been undertaken.
Studies of the abyssal tongue of Antarctic Bottom Water, which extends into the
western basin of the North Atlantic (L. Keigwin, personal communication), hint
at a LIA strengthening but as yet have yielded no definitive
evidence.</p><p>Although we have a long way to go before we will be able to get
to the bottom of this apparent dilemma, the following must be done to clarify
the situation. (<italic>i</italic>) To define the CFC-11 constraint more precisely,
measurements of the extent of saturation must be made on newly formed deep water
in both polar regions. (<italic>ii</italic>) Surveys of temperature and salinity in the
deep Atlantic Ocean made in the 1930s must be carefully compared with recent
ones in search for evidence of a shift in the position of the boundary
separating the Antarctic bottom water tongue from the overlying North Atlantic
deep water. (<italic>iii</italic>) Studies must be made of rapidly accumulating
sediments along the path of the lower limb of the Atlantic's conveyor in a
search for sedimentary anomalies associated with the LIA (see ref. <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, this issue of PNAS). (<italic>iv</italic>) More
temperature profiles must be obtained from deep holes drilled in Antarctic ice
to confirm the existence of the LIA warm anomaly (G. Clow, personal
communication).</p><p>One aspect of the debate with regard to the extent of
global warming generated by the ongoing buildup of greenhouse gases has to do
with the contribution of natural climate change. Those opposed to emission
restrictions are quick to conclude that the warming during the past century may
be dominated by the relaxation of cold LIA conditions. Although we are still a
long way from being able to assess whether or not this interpretion is correct,
were thermohaline circulation to be implicated, a step toward this goal would be
taken.</p><?mtl /hellip?></body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app><title>Appendix</title>
<sec><title>The Bipolar Seesaw.</title>
<p>The evidence for the antiphasing of the millennial-duration climate 
changes occurring on the Antarctic continent <?mtl hellip?>compared with those elsewhere on the planet comes from the correlation of the oxygen isotope records for the Antarctic Byrd and the Greenland GISP2 ice cores (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B15">15</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). This
antiphasing is clearly seen in the deglaciation interval (&#x2248;20,000 to
&#x2248;10,000 calendar years ago). During the first half of this period,
Antarctica steadily warmed, but little change occurred in Greenland. Then, at
the time when Greenland's climate underwent an abrupt warming, the warming in
Antarctica stalled. Finally, at the onset of the Y.D. cold event in Greenland,
the Antarctica warming resumed.<?mtl /hellip?></p><?mtl hellip?><p>The strongest support
for the idea that the antiphasing of climate oscillations during the period of
deglaciation was tied to changes in thermohaline circulation comes from the
temporal record of <sup>14</sup>C/C in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and upper
ocean CO<sub>2</sub>. A number of records for the Y.D. reveal a curious anomaly.
It involves rapid decrease in radiocarbon age from 11,100 to 10,500 radiocarbon
years (relative to calendar ages) during the first 20&#x0025; of the
1,200-year-long Y.D. interval followed by what seems to be a much too slow rate
of decrease from 10,500 to 10,000 years during the remaining 80&#x0025; of the
Y.D. This result suggests that, early in the Y.D., the <sup>14</sup>C/C ratio of
the atmosphere/upper ocean reservoir increased, and then, during the remainder
of the Y.D., it dropped back down. However, because in these records there was
no assurance that this pattern was not instead a product of slower deposition
rates early in the Y.D. followed by faster deposition rates, a convincing case
awaited the study of an annually layered sedimentary sequence in which the
boundaries of the Y.D. were clearly defined. Such a sequence was found in the
deep Cariaco Basin, which lies between Venezuela and the Dutch ABC Islands
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Not only are these sediments
varved, but their color is significantly lighter during the Y.D. interval. By
counting the layers and carrying out several dozen radiocarbon ages on
planktonic foraminifera contained in this sediment, it was possible (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) not only to confirm that the radiocarbon
pattern was due to changing <sup>14</sup>C/C ratio in the atmosphere/upper ocean
reservoir but also to quantify the magnitude and timing of these changes. These
results show that, during the first 200 years of the Y.D., the <sup>14</sup>C/C
ratio in surface waters of the Cariaco trench rose by 5&#x0025; and that they
then coasted back down again during the remainder of the Y.D. (Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). These <sup>14</sup>C to C ratio changes could
have been brought about either by changes in the production rate of
<sup>14</sup>C or by changes in the rate of mixing between the upper ocean and
deep ocean CO<sub>2</sub> reservoirs. However, because the <sup>14</sup>C
increase starts right at the onset of the Y.D. and because the rate of rise is
too steep to be explained by an increase in the production rate of
<sup>14</sup>C, the changes in <sup>14</sup>C to C ratio that occurred during
the Y.D. are almost certainly due to redistribution of <sup>14</sup>C. As in
today's world ocean, about three-quarters of the radiocarbon reaching the vast
deep ocean carbon reservoir does so along with the new deep waters formed in the
Northern Atlantic; were this loop in the deep ocean's ventilation system to be
shut down, the <sup>14</sup>C atoms produced by cosmic ray bombardment would be
backlogged in the atmosphere/upper ocean reservoir. Hence, such a shutdown would
not only explain the dramatic Y.D. cooling experienced in northern Europe but
also the steep rise in the <sup>14</sup>C content of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>
and upper ocean CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><fig id="F4"><caption><p>(<italic>Upper</italic>) Cariaco Trench record for the
Bolling-Allerod (BA) and Younger Dryas interval (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B18">18</xref>). DEL <sup>14</sup>C is the deviation of the recontructed
initial <sup>14</sup>C&#x002F;C from the long-term mean. (<italic>Lower</italic>)
<sup>18</sup>O records for the Greenland Ice Science Project (GISP2) and the
Byrd Station Antarctica ice cores (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B15">15</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). The time
scale is in thousands of years before present (ka).</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0204214004"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>But why did this shutdown last only 200
years? The answer is that, as deep ocean waters are being continually
dedensified by the downward mixing of the warmer overlying water, a point must
be reached at which, somewhere on the planet, waters at the surface became more
dense than those resident in the abyss. At this point, deep ventilation would be
initiated. Had this start-up occurred in the Northern Atlantic, then one might
expect that the profound Y.D. cooling therein would have been ameliorated. As
there is no evidence that such an amelioration happened, we must look elsewhere
on the globe. The logical candidate is the Southern Ocean, because the change in
circulation there could be called on to supply the heat required to propel the
warming of the Antarctic continent. Hence, the idea of the bipolar seesaw (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B4">4</xref>).</p></sec><?mtl /hellip?>
</app>
</app-group>
<ref-list><?mtl hellip?>
<ref id="B1"><citation><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Showers</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheseby</surname><given-names>M.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajdas</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><source>
Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>1257</fpage><lpage>
1266</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B2"><citation><name><surname>Keigwin</surname><given-names>L.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><source>Deep-Sea
Res.</source><year>1989</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>867
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B3"><citation><name><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>W.
S.</given-names></name><source>Paleoceanography</source><year>1998
</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>121</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B4"><citation><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>T.
F.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume>
<fpage>61</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B5"><citation><name><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>J.
M.</given-names></name><source>The Little Ice
Age</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Methuen</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref
id="B6"><citation><name><surname>Bergth&#x00F3;rsson</surname><given-names>P.
</given-names></name><source>J&#x00E0;kull</source><year>1969</year><volume>19</volume>
<fpage>94</fpage><lpage>101</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B7"><citation><name><surname>Messerli</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Messerli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>C.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Zumb&#x00FC;hl</surname><given-names>H.
J.</given-names></name><source>Arct. Alp.
Res.</source><year>1978</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>260
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B8"><citation><name><surname>Steig</surname><given-names>E.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>E.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. W.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sucher</surname><given-names>C.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>M.
L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>S.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>D.
L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>E.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clow</surname><given-names>G.
D.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage><lpage>95</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B9"><citation><name><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>W.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker
</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Fahrbach</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names
></name><name><surname>Mikolajewicz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinze
</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Peng</surname><given-names>T.-H.</given-names></name><etal/><source>J. Geophys.
Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>15833</fpage><lpage>15843</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B10"><citation><name><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>W.
S.</given-names></name><source>Oceanography</source><year>1991</year><volume>4</volume>
<fpage>79</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B11"><citation><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Visbeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broecker</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names></name><source>Inverse Methods in Global Biogeochemical
Cycles</source><year>2000</year>, Geophysical Monograph Series, eds. <name><surname>Kasibhatla</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heimann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahowald</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prinn</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name> &#x0026; <name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name> (<publisher-name>Am. Geophys. Union</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>), <volume>114</volume>, in press</citation></ref><ref
id="B12"><citation><name><surname>Orsi</surname><given-names>A.
H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullister</surname><given-names>J.
L.</given-names></name><source>Progr.
Oceanogr.</source><year>1999</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>
109</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B13"><citation><name><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>W.
S.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>286</volume>
<fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1135</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B14"><citation><name><surname>Keigwin</surname><given-names>L.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><source>Proc.
Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1342
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B15"><citation><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>M.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchardo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grootes
</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayewski</surname><given-names>P.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meese</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><source>Nature
(London)</source><year>1994</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>
666</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B16"><citation><name><surname>Jouzel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Vaikmae</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>J.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duclos
</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stievenard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name
><surname>Lorius</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toots</surname><given-names>M.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Melieres</surname><given-names>M.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burckle</surname><given-names>L.
H.</given-names></name><etal/><source>Clim.
Dyn.</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>161
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B17"><citation><name><surname>Blunier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Schwander</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stauffer</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stocker</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name><surname>D&#x00E4;llenbach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inderm&#x00FC;hle</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappellaz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname
>Raynaud</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnola</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names>
</name><source>Geophys. Res.
Lett.</source><year>1997</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2683</fpage><lpage>2686
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B18"><citation><name><surname>Hughen</surname><given-names>K.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Overpeck</surname><given-names>J.
T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>S.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashgarian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Southon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>L.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigman
</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><source>Nature
(London)</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>68
</lpage></citation></ref><?mtl /hellip?>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article> 
