<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../PublishingDTD/source_DTDs/journalpublishing.dtd">
<?mtl hellip?><article>
<!-- Monospace --><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id
journal-id-type="pubmed">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id
journal-id-type="publisher">PNAS</journal-id><issn>0027-8424</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The
National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id
pub-id-type="publisher-id">5438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677516</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group><subject>Biological
Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group>
</subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> cloning of complex
mixtures of DNA on microbeads: Physical separation of differentially expressed
cDNAs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>Sydney</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Steven
R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vermaas</surname><given-names>Eric H.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Storck</surname><given-names>Thorsten</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x2020;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>Keith</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCollum</surname><given-names>Christie</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Jen-I</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Shujun</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>James J.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eletr</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DuBridge</surname><given-names>Robert
B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burcham</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>Glenn</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff">&#x002A;</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes"
rid="FN152">&#x2021;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>&#x002A;Lynx
Therapeutics, Inc., 25861 Industrial Boulevard, Hayward, CA 94545; and
&#x2020;BASF-LYNX Bioscience, Im Neuenheimer Feld 515, Heidelberg 69120,
Germany</aff><author-notes><fn id="FN152"><p>To whom reprint
requests should be addressed. E-mail:
<email>galbrecht@lynxgen.com</email>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="com"><p>Contributed
by Sydney Brenner</p></fn>
<fn><p>Data deposition: The sequences reported
in this paper have been deposited in the GenBank database (accession nos.
&#x2013;).</p></fn>
</author-notes><pub-date
pub-type="pub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>
97</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><history><date
date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>1999</year></date>
</history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, The National Academy of
Sciences</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
<abstract><p>We describe a method for cloning nucleic acid molecules
onto the surfaces of 5-&#x03BC;m microbeads rather than in biological hosts. A
unique tag sequence is attached to each molecule, and the tagged library is
amplified. Unique tagging of the molecules is achieved by sampling a small
fraction (1&#x0025;) of a very large repertoire of tag sequences. The resulting
library is hybridized to microbeads that each carry &#x2248;10<sup>6</sup>
strands complementary to one of the tags. About 10<sup>5</sup> copies of each
molecule are collected on each microbead. Because such clones are segregated on
microbeads, they can be operated on simultaneously and then assayed separately.
To demonstrate the utility of this approach, we show how to label and extract
microbeads bearing clones differentially expressed between two libraries by
using a fluorescence-activated cell sorter (FACS). Because no prior information
about the cloned molecules is required, this process is obviously useful where
sequence databases are incomplete or nonexistent. More importantly, the process
also permits the isolation of clones that are expressed only in given tissues or
that are differentially expressed between normal and diseased states. Such
clones then may be spotted on much more cost-effective, tissue- or
disease-directed, low-density planar microarrays.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>DNA
analysis</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>parallel cloning</kwd><kwd>fluid
microarray</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>
Analysis of complex genomes requires methods for generating and fractionating
many tens of thousands of DNA fragments in quantities and formats amenable to
biochemical analysis. The difficulty of such analysis is illustrated by human
gene expression: the human genome is estimated to contain about 100,000 genes,
of which 10&#x2013;30&#x0025;, or about 20&#x2013;40 Mb, are actively expressed
in any given tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Such large numbers of expressed genes make
it difficult to track changes in expression patterns, particularly in view of
the large fraction of genes that are expressed at very low levels: it has been
estimated that as much as 30&#x0025; of mammalian messenger RNA consists of many
thousands of distinct species each making up far less than a few tenths of a
percent of the total, and typically averaging less than a few tens of copies per
cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B4">4</xref>). Yet relatively minor alterations in gene expression patterns
are associated with profound changes in cell physiology and, more broadly, in
the state of an organism's health, its longevity, and its survival (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B7">7</xref>). A variety of techniques has been developed for analyzing
gene expression that differ widely in convenience, expense, and sensitivity.
Presently, techniques based on direct sequence analysis or specific
hybridization of complex polynucleotide probes to microarrays of
oligonucleotides or polynucleotides provide the most comprehensive and sensitive
analysis of gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). However, in
both approaches, the sequences to be analyzed must either be known or cloned and
processed individually beforehand, usually with the article-id of complex robotics
systems. This makes it difficult to isolate and/or monitor many potentially
important genes that are differentially expressed at low absolute levels against
a background of more abundantly expressed genes.</p><p>To address some of these
problems, we describe an approach that greatly simplifies the handling and
analysis of complex mixtures of cDNA or genomic fragments. We show how millions
of nucleic acid molecules, amplified with one set of common primers, can be
cloned and specifically attached to 5-&#x03BC;m microbeads in a few single-tube
reactions. Central to the method is the formation of a repertoire of
oligonucleotide tags assembled combinatorially from a defined set of subunits,
or &#x201C;words,&#x201D; and their attachment to individual polynucleotides of
a complex mixture. By making the repertoire of tags large relative to the number
of polynucleotides in the mixture, samples of the tag&#x2013;polynucleotide
conjugates may be selected with virtually every polynucleotide having a unique
tag. Samples of conjugates then may be amplified and specifically hybridized to
their complementary sequences (anti-tags) on separate microbeads in a single
reaction to form a library of microbeads, each having attached a clonal
population of one polynucleotide from the original mixture.</p><p>The key
advantage of this approach over biological cloning is that the DNA on the
surface of each microbead is readily accessible for biochemical analysis without
further processing. In addition, all clones in a microbead library can be
interrogated simultaneously by analytical probes designed to assay specific
properties. This enables a broad range of applications in which clones are
identified or physically fractionated by virtue of their sequence or their
abundance or their ability to bind particular ligands. Below, we show how such
&#x201C;microbead clones&#x201D; can be used to extract differentially regulated
genes, independently of any sequence information, in the human acute monocytic
leukemia cell line, THP-1, induced by phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA) and
lipopolysaccharide (LPS). After competitive hybridization of cDNA probes from
the induced and noninduced cells, microbeads sorted on the basis of fluorescence
intensity ratios were found to carry sequences known to be up-regulated and
down-regulated in THP-1 cells after induction by PMA and LPS. Further validation
is provided by plaque hybridization with probes constructed from several genes
fractionated by our microbead procedure.</p></sec><sec
sec-type="materials/methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Construction of
Oligonucleotide Tag and Anti-Tag Libraries.</title><p>A library of 32-mer tags
was synthesized based on eight 4-mer &#x201C;words&#x201D; lacking dG described
in <italic>Results</italic> by eight rounds of &#x201C;mix and divide&#x201D;
combinatorial synthesis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) on 40
billion 5-&#x03BC;m glycidal methacrylate microbeads (Bangs Laboratories,
Carmel, IN). The microbeads were prepared with &#x2248;10&#x0025; of the initial
nucleotides linked by a base-labile group (5&#x2032;-phosphate-ON, CLONTECH). A
28-mer 3&#x2032; spacer having a primer-binding site and a <italic>Pac</italic>I site
was synthesized, followed by synthesis of the 32-mer tags and three cytidylate
residues. Five billion of these microbeads were removed and by further synthesis
a <italic>Bsp</italic>120I site and a 5&#x2032; primer-binding site were added. Aliquots
of the remaining 35 billion microbeads were prepared for capturing tagged cDNAs
as follows: 2.5 &#x00D7; 10<sup>8</sup> microbeads suspended in 100 &#x03BC;l of
H<sub>2</sub>O were combined with 100 &#x03BC;l of 10&#x00D7; NEB buffer 2 (New
England Biolabs), 10 &#x03BC;l of 100 mM ATP, 1 &#x03BC;l of 10&#x0025; Tween
20, 17 &#x03BC;l of T4 polynucleotide kinase (10 units&#x002F;&#x03BC;l), and
772 of &#x03BC;l H<sub>2</sub>O for a final volume of 1,000 &#x03BC;l. After
incubating for 2 hr at 37&#x00B0;C with vortexing, the temperature was increased
to 65&#x00B0;C for 20 min to inactivate the kinase, with continued vortexing.
After incubation, the microbeads were washed twice by spinning down the
microbeads and resuspending them in 1 ml of Tris-EDTA containing 0.01&#x0025;
Tween 20. Postsynthesis analysis of these showed that each microbead carries
about 10 million copies of a given anti-tag sequence (data not shown).</p><fig
id="F1"><caption><p>Tags were synthesized by eight rounds
of combinatorial synthesis, wherein each word,
w<sub>1</sub>&#x2013;w<sub>8</sub>, is added in a separate column of a DNA
synthesizer. In each round, a word was added to each growing tag by four
conventional base-coupling cycles, after which the microbeads were mixed and
divided for the next addition. After the eighth round, a portion of the
microbeads were separated for further synthesis of a 5&#x2032; primer-binding
site (PBS), followed by cleavage, amplification, and insertion into
pLCV1.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="pq0305438001" alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>The aliquot of
five billion microbeads was treated to cleave DNA attached by base-labile
linkers to yield a total of 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>16</sup> sequences. After
deprotection and purification by reverse-phase chromatography, sequences were
isolated by ethanol precipitation, resuspended, and used as the template for a
T7 polymerase fill-in reaction with a primer complementary to the 3&#x2032;
primer-binding site. The entire duplex then was PCR-amplified with primers
specific for the 3&#x2032; and 5&#x2032; primer-binding sites, after which the
amplicon was digested with <italic>Pac</italic>I and <italic>Bsp</italic>120I and inserted into
pLCV1 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The product was
electroporated into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to produce more than 200 million
independent chloramphenicol-resistant clones, designated pLCV2.</p><fig
id="F2"><caption><p>Attachment of tags to
cDNAs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="pq0305438002"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>cDNA Synthesis and Attachment
of Tags.</title><p>mRNA was converted to cDNA, tagged, and loaded onto
microbeads as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Briefly,
poly(A)<sup>&#x002B;</sup> RNA was extracted by using a FastTrack 2.0 kit
(Invitrogen), using the manufacturer's protocol. Double-stranded cDNA was
synthesized by using a cDNA Synthesis kit (Stratagene), using the manufacturer's
protocol with the following modifications: 2.5 &#x03BC;g of mRNA was used for
each synthesis and the primer for first strand synthesis was
5&#x2032;-biotin-GACATGCTCGTCTCTGCAT<sub>19</sub>V. After second-strand
synthesis, the cDNA was size-fractionated on a SizeSep 400 column (Amersham
Pharmacia) and ethanol-precipitated. The cDNA was resuspended and digested with
100 units of <italic>Dpn</italic>II at 37&#x00B0;C for 2 hr, after which the
biotinylated cDNA was purified with Dynal M-280 streptavidin beads. cDNA
fragments were digested off the beads by using 40 units of <italic>Bsm</italic>BI for 2
hr in an Eppendorf Thermomixer set at medium speed at 37&#x00B0;C. The
supernatant was collected, and the beads were resuspended for a second
<italic>Bsm</italic>BI digestion. cDNA fragments from the first and second digestions
were pooled, ethanol-precipitated, and resuspended in 10 &#x03BC;l of
H<sub>2</sub>0. Tag vector pLCV2 was used for loading libraries on microbeads.
pECV, which lacks tags, was used for probe libraries. The vectors were digested
with <italic>Bbs</italic>I and <italic>Bam</italic>HI and dephosphorylated, and aliquots of each
cDNA preparation were ligated with each vector. Sequences adjacent to
<italic>Bbs</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>BI were chosen to ensure compatible ends. DNA was
transformed into electro-competent <italic>E. coli</italic> TOP10 cells (Invitrogen).
Aliquots were titered on LB agar plates containing 30 &#x03BC;g/ml
chloramphenicol, and library pools were grown in liquid cultures. For the
microbead libraries, six pools of 160,000 clones each were grown in 50-ml liquid
cultures. For the probe libraries, 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>7</sup> clones were grown
in 1-liter cultures. Plasmid DNA was prepared and used for subsequent
manipulations.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbead Loading.</title><p>Tagged cDNAs
(160,000) were amplified in the presence of 5-methyl dCTP using flanking PCR
primers (designated biotin-PCR-F and FAM (6-carboxyl-fluorescein)-PCR-R;
labeling reagents from CLONTECH), and the products were digested to completion
with <italic>Pac</italic>I and affinity-purified. To expose the tags as single strands,
amplified DNA was treated with T4 polymerase in the presence of 1 mM dGTP for 60
min, thereby digesting a single strand of the tag to the GC-rich
<italic>Bsp</italic>120I site. The reaction was stopped with EDTA, and the enzyme was
denatured by heating (72&#x00B0;C for 15 min). Fifty micrograms of this mixture
then was combined with an aliquot of 16.7 million microbeads, each having about
10<sup>6</sup> copies of a single anti-tag, in a 100-&#x03BC;l reaction
containing 500 mM NaCl, 10 mM sodium phosphate, 0.01&#x0025; Tween 20, and
3&#x0025; dextran sulfate. The sample was incubated for 3 days at 72&#x00B0;C.
The microbeads then were washed twice, first in 50 mM Tris, 50 mM NaCl, 3 mM
Mg<sub>2</sub>Cl, and then in 10 mM Tris&#x00B7;HCl (pH 8), 1 mM EDTA,
0.01&#x0025; Tween 20, after which the 1&#x0025; brightest beads were sorted on
a Cytomation MoFlo cytometer. cDNAs (10<sup>4</sup>-10<sup>5</sup> per
microbead) were loaded, determined by comparing the amount of test probe
hybridized to saturation to 2,000 identical microbeads with known amounts of the
test probe after elution and electrophoretic separation (data not shown).
Loaded, sorted microbeads were treated with T4 DNA polymerase in the presence of
0.1 mM dNTP for 30 min at 12&#x00B0;C to fill in any gaps between the hybridized
conjugate and the 5&#x2032; end of the anti-tag. The reaction was stopped by
washing in buffer containing 10 mM Tris&#x00B7;HCl (pH 8), 1 mM EDTA, and
0.01&#x0025; Tween 20, after which the microbeads were treated with Pronase
(Boehringer Mannheim) at a final concentration of 0.14
&#x03BC;g&#x002F;&#x03BC;l in PBS containing 0.01&#x0025; Tween 20, and
incubated for 60 min at 37&#x00B0;C. The anti-tag was ligated to the cDNA by
treating with T4 DNA ligase in the presence of 1 mM ATP for 60 min at
37&#x00B0;C. After washing and Pronase treatment, the fluorescent label was
switched to the noncovalently attached strand by digesting the DNA with
<italic>Dpn</italic>II, treating with Pronase, treating with phosphatase, and ligating
an adaptor carrying a 3&#x2032; FAM label. A 14-bp adaptor having a
phosphorylated 5&#x2032; <italic>Dpn</italic>II-compatible end and a 3&#x2032;-FAM label
was ligated in a conventional ligation reaction, after which the microbeads were
washed once with PBS containing 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> and treated with Pronase.
The remaining nick was ligated by treatment with T4 polynucleotide kinase and T4
DNA ligase, after which the microbeads were washed once with PBS containing 1 mM
CaCl<sub>2</sub>, treated with Pronase, and washed twice with Tris-EDTA/Tween.
Noncovalently attached strands were removed by treatment with 150 mM
NaOH.</p></sec><sec><title>Probe Synthesis and Competitive
Hybridization.</title><p>cDNA-containing plasmid libraries from induced and
noninduced THP-1 cells were linearized, and probes were prepared by runoff
synthesis. Twenty micrograms each of the probe libraries was digested with
<italic>Sau</italic>3A. Thirty-five rounds of linear amplification with either R110 dUTP
(Perkin&#x2013;Elmer) or Cy5 dUTP (Amersham Pharmacia) were performed. The
strands complementary to the DNA covalently attached to reference microbeads
(described below) were melted off with two 0.5 ml of 150 mM NaOH washes at room
temperature for 15 min with mild vortexing, after which the microbeads were
washed twice in 0.5 ml of 4&#x00D7; SSC 0.1&#x0025; SDS. Ten micrograms of each
probe then was mixed with the microbeads in 50 &#x03BC;l of 4&#x00D7; SSC
0.1&#x0025; SDS, heated to 80&#x00B0;C for 3 min, and then cooled to
65&#x00B0;C. After 16 hr with constant mixing, the microbeads were quenched in
10 ml of Tris-EDTA/Tween on ice, rinsed with 1&#x00D7; SSC/0.1&#x0025; SDS,
resuspended in 0.5 ml of 1&#x00D7; SSC/0.1&#x0025;SDS, and finally washed in
0.1&#x00D7; SSC/0.1&#x0025; SDS at 65&#x00B0;C for 15 min. Labeled microbeads
were sorted with a Coulter EPICS Elite ESP flow
cytometer.</p></sec><sec><title>PCR, Cloning, and Sequencing of Isolated
cDNA.</title><p>Sorted microbeads were used directly in a PCR, and the product
was cloned by using the TA Cloning procedure (Invitrogen) and
sequenced.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture.</title><p>THP-1 cells (ATCC
accession no. TIB-202) were grown in DMEM/F-12 media supplemented with
10&#x0025; heat-inactivated FBS (56&#x00B0;C, 30 min), 5 &#x00D7;
10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> M 2-mercaptoethanol, 100 units/ml penicillin, and 100
&#x03BC;g/ml streptomycin. Cultures seeded with 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells
per ml were grown to a cell density of 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells per ml
(approximately 4 days). Cells were induced by adding PMA (stock concentration 1
mM in DMSO) to a final concentration of 100 nM and were grown for 48 hr with
PMA. DMSO was added to noninduced cells. During this period, approximately
80&#x0025; of the PMA-treated cells became adherent, whereas about 20&#x0025;
remained in suspension. After 48 hr, the medium and nonadherent cells were
removed from PMA-induced cells and replaced with fresh medium containing 5
&#x03BC;g/ml LPS from <italic>E. coli</italic> serotype 0111:B4 (Sigma). Control cells
were pelleted by centrifugation at 1,400 &#x00D7; <italic>g</italic> for 4 min and
resuspended in fresh equilibrated medium, and incubation continued. The cells
were harvested after 4 hr. Adherent PMA- and LPS-treated cells were dislodged by
using a cell scraper and pelleted by centrifugation at 1,400 &#x00D7;
<italic>g</italic>. Control cells, which remained in suspension, were simply
pelleted.</p></sec></sec><sec
sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Principle of the
Method.</title><p>Each nucleic acid molecule in a complex mixture first is
labeled with an oligonucleotide tag, after which a sample of the resulting
library of tag&#x2013;molecule conjugates is amplified. After amplification, a
sample of <italic>n</italic> molecules will yield a library containing <italic>n</italic>
families of clones, each identified by a unique tag. This permits them to be
collected on a microbead that carries the complement (anti-tag) to a family's
unique tag. Thus, a mixture of 1,000,000 molecules can be converted into a
library of about as many microbeads, each carrying about 100,000 copies of one
of the templates. To achieve this, the nucleic acid sequences used as tags and
anti-tags must be chosen to maximize the efficiency and discrimination of
hybridization of a given clone to a given microbead.</p><p>Six criteria were
used to design the repertoire of tags: (<italic>i</italic>) the repertoire must be
diverse enough to enable the unique tagging of all (or nearly all) the molecules
in large libraries; (<italic>ii</italic>) the tags must remain physically attached to
the tagged molecules after operations such as cleavage by restriction enzymes;
(<italic>iii</italic>) the melting temperatures (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) of all
tag/anti-tag duplexes must be isothermal; (<italic>iv</italic>) the difference in
<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> between any perfectly matched tag/anti-tag duplex and any
duplex with a single mismatch must be both the same for all sequences and large
enough to discriminate strongly in favor of the perfect match; (<italic>v</italic>) a
practical and effective manner must exist to enable construction of such a
repertoire; and (<italic>vi</italic>) there must be a simple way of applying the method,
in parallel, and in one reaction, to any ensemble of nucleic acid molecules. A
library of sequences with these properties can be constructed from a special DNA
language with a vocabulary made up of eight four-base &#x201C;words&#x201D;:
TTAC, AATC, TACT, ATCA, ACAT, TCTA, CTTT, and CAAA.</p><p>Each word uses only
three (A, T, and C) of the DNA bases and differs from all of the other words in
three of the four bases, and they all form, with their respective complements,
three A:T and one G:C base pairs. Limiting the composition of the
four-nucleotide words to three bases eliminates self-complementarity within any
sequence made up of the words and prevents their cleavage by any restriction
enzyme with symmetrical recognition sites containing both G and C. The
repertoire of tags is constructed by a &#x201C;mix and divide&#x201D;
combinatorial synthesis of all possible eight-word combinations. There are
8<sup>8</sup> such combinations, forming a tag repertoire of 16,777,216
sequences 32 bases long. 
<?mtl /hellip?>An example of one tag and its anti-tag complement is shown 
below:</p>
<p><monospace>5&#x2032;-TACT.TTAC.ACAT.ATCA.CTTT.CTTT.CAAA.AATC-3&#x2032; </monospace></p>
<p><monospace>3&#x2032;-ATGA.AATG.TGTA.TAGT.GAAA.GAAA.GTTT.TTAG-5&#x2032;</monospace>
</p>
<p>Because of the words used to construct the tag repertoire<?mtl hellip?>, all
16,777,216 eight-word tag/anti-tag duplexes have the same base pair composition,
i.e., 24 A:T and eight G:C base pairs. Consequently, all of the tags in the
entire repertoire should have about the same <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>. Because all
tag sequences differ from their nearest neighbors by at least one word, or three
base mismatches, there is good discrimination between perfect matches and
one-word mismatches. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref><italic>A</italic>
depicts the melting curves of eight-word duplexes that have zero-, one-, or
two-word mismatches. It shows that at 68&#x00B0;C, a duplex with a single-word
mismatch dissociates, whereas the duplex with an exact match does not. Fig.
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref><italic>B</italic> shows that anti-tags
immobilized on a solid surface do not lose their ability to discriminate in
favor of the correct tags in hybridization experiments. To estimate the accuracy
of loading, we deposited individual microbeads into 96-well microtiter plates by
using fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) and subjected them to multiple
rounds of PCR amplification. Ten percent of the wells produced no detectable
product, 70&#x0025; yielded single bands on an agarose gel, and the remaining
20&#x0025; yielded more than one band (data not shown). Of this latter category,
one-fourth were estimated to have contained two microbeads; we estimate,
therefore, that at least 85&#x0025; of the microbeads contain only one sequence.
</p><fig id="F3"><caption><p>Melting curve of tags with
complements. (<italic>A</italic>) Approximately 0.35 OD units of each double-stranded
oligonucleotide was resuspended in 10 mM sodium phosphate, pH 7.6/50 mM NaCl/3
mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. The samples were heated at 1&#x00B0;C per min, and the OD
at 260 nm was measured and recorded. Reactions consisted of one common
oligonucleotide, cccatcactttatcaatcaacatatcacaaaaatctcc, and a second
oligonucleotide as follows: perfect match, (&#xE00C;)
ggagatttttgtgatatgttgattgataaagtgatggg; one-word mismatch, (&#x25CB;)
gga<italic>tgat</italic>tttgtgatatgttgattgataaagtgatggg; two-word mismatch, (&#x25B5;)
ggagatttttgt<italic>ttga</italic>tgtt<italic>ttgt</italic>gataaagtgatggg. (<italic>B</italic>)
Microbeads bearing the oligonucleotide ggagatttttgtgatatgttgattgataaagtgatggg
were loaded with FAM-labeled cDNA tagged with this sequence. In separate tubes,
three cDNAs whose tags differed at the first, third, or fifth positions also
were loaded. The samples then were washed in 50 mM Tris/50 mM NaCl/3 mM
Mg<sub>2</sub>Cl at increasing temperatures as indicated. Microbeads then were
analyzed by FACS, and the means of fluorescence intensities were plotted for the
perfect match of the tag (filled bar), the mismatches (gray bars), and the
ratios (cross-hatched bar) of the perfect signal to the average noise of the
three mismatches.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0305438003"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>Allocation of tags to individual molecules
is outlined in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. First, the complete
repertoire of tags in a plasmid library is ligated to the entire population of
cDNAs to give a population of tag&#x2013;cDNA conjugates that contains a
conjugate between every tag and every cDNA. Next, a sample of 160,000
tag&#x2013;cDNA conjugates is taken that includes only 1&#x0025; of the full
repertoire and, thus, the probability that two different cDNAs will have the
same tag sequence is very small, about 0.01&#x0025;. The vast majority will be
uniquely tagged. The small sample size also ensures greater specificity in
hybridization, because most of the sampled tags are likely to differ from one
another by two or more words. The 160,000 tag&#x2013;cDNA conjugates are
amplified by PCR to give fluorescently labeled biotinylated amplicons. After
purification with a streptavidinated support, the DNA is treated with T4 DNA
polymerase in the presence of dGTP to remove one strand from the tag/anti-tag
duplex using the 3&#x2032; &#x2192; 5&#x2032; exonuclease and exchange reaction
activities of the enzyme. The resulting tag&#x2013;cDNA conjugates are loaded
onto microbeads by mixing them with the full 16.7 million repertoire of
microbeads, each carrying a specific anti-tag sequence. The loading reaction is
carried out under equilibrium conditions (i.e., 72 hr at 72&#x00B0;C) to ensure
that hybridization discrimination is achieved through the higher off-rate of
mismatched sequences. After separating loaded microbeads from unloaded
microbeads by FACS, as shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, the
hybridized DNA is ligated to the anti-tag, covalently attaching one strand of
the DNA to the microbead's surface. This permits easy removal of the
noncovalently attached strand.</p><fig id="F4"><caption><p>Two-parameter, 530-nm (PMT1) and 666-nm (PMT2), FACS
contour plot showing separation of loaded microbeads (contour on right) from
unloaded microbeads (contour on left).</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pq0305438004"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Differential Gene
Expression.</title><p>To illustrate the first of several applications of our
cloning methodology, we describe an experiment for physically extracting clones
that are differentially represented in two libraries. After melting off the
noncovalently attached DNA strands from the microbeads, the remaining strands
are available for competitive hybridization with two probes labeled with
different fluorophores, to produce, in effect, a fluid microarray of millions of
microbeads. The ratio of probes hybridizing to each bead can easily be measured
at high throughput (20,000 beads per sec) by using available FACS equipment.
Thus, microbeads labeled with more of one fluorophore than the other can be
easily identified and physically separated from the rest of the
library.</p><p>The sensitivity of this approach was tested in an experiment
where two fluorescent probes in ratios of 1:8, 8:1, 1:4, 4:1, 1:2, 2:1, 1:1,
0:1, and 1:0 were hybridized to a complementary set of microbeads. The results
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) show that the probe ratios can be
clearly measured and that differences as low as 2-fold can be detected. The
range of fluorescence intensities exhibited by the microbeads reflects the
variation in the number of cDNAs loaded on each microbead, which determines the
total number of probe molecules that can bind.</p><fig id="F5"><caption><p>Model system for two-color competitive hybridization. A
34-mer, ggagatttgataaagtttgatgtgtaatagaggg, was synthesized with a 3&#x2032; FAM
or Cy5 label. The oligonucleotides were brought to final concentration of 14
&#x03BC;M in 30 &#x03BC;l. The two labeled oligonucleotides were combined in
nine separate mixtures in ratios of 1:0, 8:1, 4:1, 2:1, 1:1, 1:2, 1:4, 1:8, and
0:1. Hybridization of each mixture to 100,000 microbeads bearing the
complementary oligonucleotide was performed, and 10,000 microbeads from each of
the mixtures were analyzed with a Coulter Elite Flow Cytometer using 488-nm and
633-nm lasers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="pq0305438005" alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>To see whether we
could enrich for differentially expressed genes by using FACS, we made a
microbead library with cDNA pooled from THP-1 before and after treatment with
PMA and LPS. Four cDNA probes were constructed: two from the same library of
induced cDNAs, which were labeled with either R110 or Cy5, and one each from
libraries of induced and noninduced cDNAs, which were labeled, respectively,
with Cy5 and R110. The former were used in a control experiment to compare the
library with itself. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref><italic>A</italic> is a
FACS plot of the microbead library hybridized with a 1:1 mixture of differently
labeled probes from the same library, whereas Fig. <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F6">6</xref><italic>B</italic> is a plot of the microbead library hybridized with a
1:1 mixture of cDNA probes from the induced and noninduced cells. The
distribution of microbeads in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F6">6</xref><italic>A</italic> allowed us to set gates for collecting microbeads
that were more heavily labeled with either Cy5 or R110 (Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref><italic>B</italic>). The triangles in Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref><italic>B</italic> represent the gates from which
microbeads carrying up-regulated or down-regulated clones were collected. Each
gate was set to collect about 1&#x0025; of the total number of clones in the
library: gate 1 should collect clones that are 10-fold or more up-regulated,
whereas gate 2 should collect clones that are 2-fold or more down-regulated.
</p><fig id="F6"><caption><p>A reference library of
2,000,000 microbeads was formed by mixing equal numbers of microbeads with
attached cDNA derived from induced and noninduced THP-1 cells. Reference
microbeads (100,000) were hybridized with 10 &#x03BC;g each of Cy5-labeled probe
and R110-labeled probe, both derived from the same induced library to yield
<italic>A</italic>. Microbeads (1,600,000) were hybridized with 10 &#x03BC;g of
Cy5-labeled probe from the induced library and 10 &#x03BC;g of R110-labeled
probe derived from the noninduced library to yield
<italic>B</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="pq0305438006" alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>Of the 1,600,100
microbeads used in this experiment, 13,988 (0.87&#x0025;) were collected in the
up-regulated fraction, and 17,303 (1.01&#x0025;) in the down-regulated fraction.
The DNA in these fractions was recovered by PCR, and 956 of the up-regulated
clones and 985 of the down-regulated clones were sequenced. Clones from the
up-regulated fraction included 68 known genes, 35 expressed sequence tags, and
nine novel sequences, whereas clones from the down-regulated fraction included
209 known genes, 111 expressed sequence tags, and five novel sequences. In the
up-regulated fraction there were many known PMA-induced genes such as IL-8,
tumor necrosis factor &#x03B1;, macrophage inflammatory protein 1, and
superoxide dismutase 2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>&#x2013;<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). There was very little overlap between the
up- and down-regulated sets of genes, except for the presence of a small number
of microbeads bearing up-regulated B94 (M92357) cDNAs in the down-regulated
fraction and some microbeads bearing down-regulated 23 kDa basic protein
transcript (X56932) in the up-regulated fraction. These were likely the result
of sorting errors caused by clustering of microbeads in adjacent
drops.</p></sec><sec><title>Plaque Hybridizations.</title><p>To validate our
procedure, we independently cloned cDNA from the induced and noninduced THP-1
cells in bacteriophage lambda and screened filters each containing 50,000
plaques with probes derived from 19 of the genes identified by sequencing the
DNA from the fractionated beads. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>
summarizes these results. In every case, the sequences derived from beads
collected in gates 1 or 2 were shown to be either up-regulated 29- to 500-fold
or down-regulated 2- to 16-fold, respectively. These changes spanned expression
levels of 0.02&#x2013;2&#x0025;.</p><table-wrap id="T1"><caption><p>THP-1 expression levels by plaque hybridization
assays</p></caption><table><tr><th>GeneBank
Number</th><th>Gene</th><th>Noninduced, replicate counts</th><th>PMA/LPS
induced, replicate counts</th><th>Up- or down-regulation </th></tr><tr><td
colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Up-regulated genes (Gate
1)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="Y00787"/></td><td>IL-8</td><td>1 /0</td><td>663
/808</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link
ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="X65965"/></td><td>SOD-2</td><td>0 /0</td><td>1636
/1096</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link
ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="M25315"/></td><td>MIP-1</td><td>0 /0</td><td>1120
</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="J04130"/></td><td>Act-2</td><td>0
/0</td><td>453/542/572/606</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="X02910"/></td><td>TNF-&#x03B1;</td><td>0 /0</td><td>81
/82</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="J03210"/></td><td>Collagenase type IV</td><td>0 /0</td><td>92
/93</td><td>&#x003E;500&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="M21121"/></td><td>RANTES</td><td>0 /7</td><td>113
/92</td><td>29&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="M92357"/></td><td>B94</td><td>7/3/0/2
</td><td>155/150/124/174</td><td>50&#x00D7;</td></tr><tr><td>Down-regulated
genes (Gate 2) </td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="X13546"/></td><td>HMG-17</td><td>75 /83</td><td>6
/4</td><td>15.8&#x00D7; </td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="M17885"/></td><td>Acidic
ribosomal protein P0</td><td>191 /195</td><td>84 /54</td><td>2.8&#x00D7;
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="X16869"/></td><td>Elongation factor 1&#x03B1;</td><td>577
/607</td><td>268 /270</td><td>2.2&#x00D7;</td></tr></table></table-wrap><p>THP-1 cells
respond to PMA by first coming out of the cell cycle followed by the induction
of the genes required for differentiation. The first process should be
associated with the down-regulation of a large number of genes involved in the
growth of cells, such as ribosomal protein-coding genes. Plaque hybridization
with several genes in this class indicates that these are down-regulated between
2- and 4-fold (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Our method detects
these relatively small changes; we found an enrichment of these cDNAs in the
pool of microbeads collected in gate 2. Of the 989 clones sequenced, 375 could
be assigned to 48 ribosomal proteins with recurrences ranging from 1 to 42 and
an average of 7.8 per gene. We estimate the enrichment to be 5&#x00D7;. In
addition, the pool of microbeads in gate 2 was not significantly contaminated by
genes that were unaffected by PMA stimulation (data not
shown).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have
described a method for cloning libraries of DNA fragments on the surfaces of
microbeads and have shown how this method facilitates identification and
physical extraction of genes that are differentially expressed. Microbead clones
can be processed in parallel in a single tube, and there is no need to handle
each clone separately for analysis and retrieval. Because the DNA on microbeads
is accessible for direct interrogation, no further biochemical processing is
required for various types of analyses, such as hybridization or
sequencing.</p><p>Our ability to generate a million or more microbeads carrying
clones from very large cDNA libraries allows the selection of sequences
differentially regulated at very low levels. All that is necessary is that the
microbead library be large enough to contain nearly all of the sequences from
the libraries being compared. No previous knowledge of any of the sequences is
required. Nucleic acid samples therefore can be from any source. The microbead
libraries used for comparisons are constructed from a combination of the
libraries being analyzed. Probes are constructed separately from the libraries
and are labeled differentially. The ratio with which probes hybridize to the
microbeads is equally accurate for microbeads carrying rare and abundant
species, because each microbead responds to the probes independently of how many
others carry the same cDNA.</p><p>Most importantly, our method allows libraries
to be probed very deeply, much more deeply than is practical by other methods.
To attempt identification of differentially expressed clones by deep, random,
expressed sequence tag sequencing of the libraries being compared would be
prohibitive. To do so with high-density planar microarrays (chips or gridded
clones on filters) would require access to chips or filters containing all
sequences expressed by the system and, even then, might not adequately detect
low abundance genes. To do so with serial analysis of gene expression
experiments limited to 2,000 sequencing runs (the same number we used) would be
equivalent to probing only about 50,000 signatures deep whereas our extracted,
differentially expressed, clones were the result of probing the libraries
2,000,000 deep. Because our technique readily selects out a much-reduced set of
clones relevant to a biological system or an experiment, it can be deployed as a
discovery tool that enables easier and more effective uses of other
techniques.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Laurie J. Goodman, Holger
Hiemisch, Hans Christian Kornau, An Lai, Ling Yau, Jason Zeng, and Eugene A.
Zhukovsky for their assistance in this
project.</p></ack><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term
id="G1">PMA</term><def><p>phorbol 12-myristate
13-acetate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term
id="G2">LPS</term><def><p>lipopolysaccharide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term
id="G3">FACS</term><def><p>fluorescence-activated cell
sorting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term
id="G4">FAM</term><def><p>6-carboxyl-fluorescein</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</glossary><ref-list><ref
id="B1"><citation><name><surname>Antequera</surname><given-names>F.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>11995</fpage><lpage>11999
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B2"><citation><name><surname>Rowen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahairas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>L.
</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>
605</fpage><lpage>607</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B3"><citation><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>J.
O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>J.
G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Richardson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><source>Nature
(London)</source><year>1974</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>
204</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B4"><citation><name><surname>Ostrow</surname><given-names>R.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>W.
G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosika</surname><given-names>G.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faras</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><source>Biochim.
Biophys.
Acta</source><year>1979</year><volume>562</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>102
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B5"><citation><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klopp</surname><given-names>R.
G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weindruch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Prolla</surname><given-names>T.
A.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume>
<fpage>1390</fpage><lpage>1393</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B6"><citation><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velculescu</surname><given-names>V.
E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>S.
E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hruban</surname><given-names>R.
H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>S.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Kinzler</surname><given-names>K.
W.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>276</volume>
<fpage>1268</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B7"><citation><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>T.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slonim</surname><given-names>D.
K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huard
</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaasenbeek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name
><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>J.
P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coller</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname
><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>J.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caligiuri</surname><given-names>M.
A.</given-names></name><etal/><source>Science</source><year>1999
</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>537</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B8"><citation><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><source>Genome
Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>995
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B9"><citation><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>J.
L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>V.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P.
O.</given-names></name><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume>
<fpage>680</fpage><lpage>686</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x0026; <name><surname>DuBridge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <year>1999</year> PCT Publication WO
99/35293</citation></ref><ref
id="B11"><citation><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>C.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><source>FEBS
Lett.</source><year>1993</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>298
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B12"><citation><name><surname>Gatanaga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>C.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatanaga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Cappuccini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>R.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><source>Cell.
Immunol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B13"><citation><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nomiyama</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>K.
</given-names></name><source>Mol. Cell.
Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>658
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B14"><citation><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.
Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haran</surname><given-names>V.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikkappa
</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>F.
B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>P.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsan</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><source>Am. J.
Physiol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>C740</fpage><lpage>
C747</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> <?mtl /hellip?>
