<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../../Ncbi/ArchivingDTD/DTD/Working/archivearticle.dtd">
<?mtl hellip?>
<article>
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jcm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed">J Clin
Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">J CLIN
MICROBIOL</journal-id><issn>0095-1137</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for
Microbiology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id
pub-id-type="publisher-id">1513</article-id><article-id
pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.39.7.2485-2493.2001</article-id><article-id
pub-id-type="pmid">11427558</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group><subject>Mycobacteriology and Aerobic
Actinomycetes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Serological
Expression Cloning and Immunological Evaluation of MTB48, a Novel
<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>
Antigen</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lodes</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes"
rid="FN150">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>Davin C.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamath</surname><given-names>Raodoh</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>Craig H.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>Darin R.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>Lisa D.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>Diana
Pedral</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Skeiky</surname><given-names>Yasir A.
W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Badaro</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Persing</surname><given-names>David H.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>Steven G.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>Raymond
L.</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><sup>1</sup>Corixa
Corporation<sup>1</sup> and<sup>3</sup> Infectious Disease Research
Institute,<sup>3</sup> Seattle, Washington 98104; <sup>4</sup>Department of
Pathobiology, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington 98195<sup>4</sup>;
and <sup>2</sup>University of Bahia, Salvador,
Brazil<sup>2</sup></aff><author-notes><fn id="FN150"
symbol="&#x002A;"><p>Corresponding author. Mailing address: Corixa Corporation,
1124 Columbia St., Suite 200, Seattle, WA 98104. Phone: (206) 754-5797. Fax:
(206) 754-5715. E-mail:
<email>lodes@corixa.com</email>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date
pub-type="pub"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>39
</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2485</fpage><lpage>2493</lpage><history><date
date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2000</year></date><date
date-type="rev-request"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2001</year></date>
<date
date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2001</year></date>
</history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2001, American Society for
Microbiology</copyright-statement><abstract><p>Improved diagnostics are needed for the detection of
<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis,</italic> especially for patients with smear-negative
disease. To address this problem, we have screened <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
(H37Rv and Erdman strains) genomic expression libraries with pooled sera from
patients with extrapulmonary disease and with sera from patients with elevated
reactivity with <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> lysate. Both serum pools were reactive
with clones expressing a recombinant protein referred to here as MTB48. The
genomic sequence of the resulting clones was identical to that of the <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv isolate and showed 99&#x0025; identity to the
<italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> and <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG isolate sequences. The
genomic location of this sequence is 826 bp upstream of a region containing the
<italic>esat-6</italic> gene that is deleted in the <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG isolate. The
<italic>mtb48</italic> 1,380-bp open reading frame encodes a predicted 47.6-kDa
polypeptide with no known function. Southern and Western blot analyses indicate
that this sequence is present in a single copy and is conserved in the <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. bovis</italic> isolates tested but not in other
mycobacterial species tested, including <italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic> and
<italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic>. In addition, the native protein was detected in
the cytoplasm, as was a processed form that was also shed into the medium during
culture. Serological analysis of recombinant MTB48 and the <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> 38-kDa antigen with a panel of patient and control sera
indicates that the inclusion of recombinant MTB48 in a prototype serodiagnostic
test increases assay sensitivity for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infection when it
is combined with other known immunodominant antigens, such as the 38-kDa
antigen.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>
Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> continues to be the major infectious cause of
human death in developing countries and has reemerged in industrialized
countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B28">28</xref>). This reemergence is due, in part, to infection with the
human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which has led to increased susceptibility to
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and active disease (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>), development of
new strains of multiple-drug-resistant <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>),
and reduced resources for treatment and surveillance of patients (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>).
Control of this infection will depend on new antibiotic therapy, improved early
detection for both smear-positive and -negative cases, and the development of an
effective vaccine. The development of a sensitive rapid serodiagnostic test
would complement present methods of diagnosis, including skin testing, DNA
amplification, bacterial culture, and radiological imaging and has become a
major research goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). A rapid and
inexpensive assay could reduce the need for the more expensive tests, possibly
reducing the cost of diagnosis, and would be of value in an emergency room
setting, where early knowledge of a patient's disease status would be helpful.
Finally, an inexpensive diagnostic test is needed in developing countries, where
more expensive diagnostic tools are not available. To date, many <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> antigens, such as the 38-kDa lipoglycoprotein (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), MTC28 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B25">25</xref>), MPT32 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), MTB81
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), CFP-10 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B9">9</xref>), and the 19-kDa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and
14-kDa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>) antigens, have been tested
for their utilities in the development of a rapid serodiagnostic test (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). However, the sensitivity needed for
a useful test has not been achieved due to the heterogeneous human response to
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> antigens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>)
and to the low seroreactivities of problematic groups, such as HIV-positive
patients or those with smear-negative disease (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Here we describe the cloning of
<italic>mtb48</italic> by screening a <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> genomic expression
library with pooled sera from patients with extrapulmonary disease and with sera
from patients with elevated reactivity with <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> lysate. The
<italic>mtb48</italic> 1,380-bp open reading frame (ORF) encodes a predicted 47.6-kDa
polypeptide with no known function. Southern blot and bioinformatic analyses
indicate that this sequence is present as a single copy and is highly conserved
in the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> isolates tested
but not in other mycobacterial species tested, including <italic>Mycobacterium
leprae</italic> and <italic>Mycobacterium avium.</italic> Western blot analysis shows that
the native protein is cytoplasmic and not membrane bound. A truncated form of
the native protein is found both in the cytoplasm and in the culture filtrate
(culture filtrate protein &#x005B;CFP&#x005D;), indicating that this form could
be shed. Because serological reactivity to MTB48 is complementary to that of
other <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> antigens, this new antigen adds significantly to
the antigen pool that will be needed for a highly sensitive and specific
serodiagnostic test.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials/methods"><title>MATERIALS AND
METHODS</title><sec><title>Mycobacterial strains.</title><p>Sean Skerritt
(Seattle Veterans Affairs Hospital, Seattle, Wash.) provided <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> strains H37Ra (ATCC 25177), H37Rv, and Erdman (ATCC 35801).
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strain C is a clinical isolate provided by Lee Riley
(University of California, Berkeley). Pelleted samples of <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG
and <italic>M. leprae</italic> were provided by Paul Tan (Genesis Corp., Auckland, New
Zealand). Other species of mycobacteria, including <italic>Mycobacterium
scrofulaceum</italic> (ATCC 19981), <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> (ATCC 19420),
<italic>Mycobacterium fortuitum</italic> (ATCC 6841), <italic>Mycobacterium malmoense</italic>
(ATCC 29571), and <italic>Mycobacterium gordonae</italic> (ATCC 14470), were obtained
from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC; Manassas,
Va.).</p></sec><sec><title>Library preparation and serological expression
screening.</title><p><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cells were lysed in phenol with a
cell disrupter (Mini-Beadbeater; type BX-4; Biospec Products, Bartlesville,
Okla.) following the manufacturer's instructions. After the addition of TE
buffer (10 mM Tris, 1 mM EDTA &#x005B;pH 8&#x005D;), the lysate was extracted
two times with phenol, followed by extraction with phenol-chloroform-isoamyl
alcohol and chloroform. Twenty micrograms each of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
Erdman and H37Rv strain genomic DNA was sheared with a sonicator (B. Braun
Biotech, Inc., Allentown, Pa.) to generate fragments of approximately 0.5 to 5.0
kbp. DNA fragments were blunted with T4 DNA polymerase (Gibco BRL, Grand Island,
N.Y.) and ligated to <italic>Eco</italic>RI adapters (Stratagene, La Jolla, Calif.).
Adapted inserts were then phosphorylated with T4 polynucleotide kinase
(Stratagene) and size selected with a Sephacryl S-400 HR column (Sigma Chemical
Co., St. Louis, Mo.). Insert DNA was ligated to a Lambda ZAP II,
<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested, calf intestinal alkaline phosphatase-treated vector
(Stratagene), and the ligation mixture was packaged with Gigapack II Gold
packaging extract (Stratagene).</p><p>Immunoreactive proteins were screened from
approximately 5 &#x00D7; 10<sup>5</sup> PFU of recombinant lambda phage from
both the Erdman and the H37Rv genomic expression libraries with nitrocellulose
filters (Schleicher &#x0026; Schuell, Keene, N.H.). Reactive plaques were
assessed with two pools of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>-adsorbed patient sera. The
first was a pool of three patient serum samples that were strongly reactive with
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> lysate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), as
assessed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) (H37Rv library; TbH
clones), and the second was a pool of five serum samples from <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic>-infected patients with extrapulmonary disease (Erdman library;
XP clones). Positive plaques were visualized with an alkaline
phosphatase-conjugated goat anti-human immunoglobulin G (IgG), IgA, and IgM
(heavy and light chain) secondary antibodies (Zymed Laboratories Inc., South San
Francisco, Calif.) developed with nitroblue
tetrazolium&#x2013;5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolylphosphate (Gibco BRL). Excision of
phagemid was done by the Lambda ZAP II protocol, and the resulting plasmid DNA
was sequenced with an ABI 377 automated sequencer (Perkin-Elmer/ABI, Foster
City, Calif.) with M13 forward, reverse, and specific internal DNA sequencing
primers. Nucleic acid and protein homology searches were performed with software
from DNASTAR, Inc. (Madison, Wis.) against the EMBL and GenBank database and the
Swiss and PIR and Translated database. Protein analysis was performed with the
PSORT program (National Institute for Basic Biology, Okazaki, Japan) and Protean
analysis software from DNASTAR, Inc., including the Kyte-Doolittle
hydrophilicity plot, Jameson-Wolf antigenicity index, and Emini surface
probability plot.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression and purification of
recombinant antigens.</title><p>Four recombinant antigens were generated,
including the amino terminus (rTbH4), the carboxy terminus (rXP-1), and the
full-length sequence (rMTB48) of MTB48, as well as the mature polypeptide for
the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> 38-kDa antigen (r38 kDa). Expression of rTbH4,
rXP-1, and r38 kDa was accomplished by amplifying a plasmid insert (TbH4 and
XP-1) or <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> Erdman genomic DNA (38 kDa) with <italic>Pfu</italic>
polymerase (Stratagene) and clone-specific primers that included a 5&#x2032;
<italic>Nde</italic>I restriction site (in italics in the sequences below), an ATG
initiation codon (underlined in the sequences below), and a nucleotide sequence
coding for 6 histidines (boldface in the sequences below) and a 3&#x2032; primer
with a stop codon and a <italic>Hin</italic>dIII or <italic>Eco</italic>RI restriction site
(italic in the sequences below). 
<?mtl /hellip?>Oligonucleotide primers for the amplification of TbH4 included
5&#x2032;-ATTAGGT<italic>CAT</italic><underline><italic>ATG</italic>
</underline><bold>CACCATCACCATCACCAT</bold>ACGCAGTCGCAGACCGTGACGG and
3&#x2032;-TATAGG<italic>AAGCTT</italic>CTAATCCTCGGTGTAGAGCGCCTCG. XP-1 was 
amplified with 5&#x2032;-CAATTA<italic>CAT</italic><underline>
<italic>ATG</italic></underline><bold>CATCACCATCACCATCAC</bold>
AACGACGGCGAAGGAACTGTGC and 3&#x2032;-AACCTG<italic>GAATTC</italic>GTCCATGCTCACTTCGAC,
and the 38-kDa antigen was amplified with 5&#x2032;-CAATTA<italic>CAT</italic>
<underline><italic>ATG</italic></underline><bold>CATCACCATCACCATCAC</bold>
TGTGGCTCGAAACCACCGAGC and<?mtl hellip?>3&#x2032;-GTACG<italic>GAATTC</italic>GTGGTCAACGAGGCTAGCTGG. Amplification
product was digested with the appropriate restriction enzymes, isolated by gel
electrophoresis, and ligated into a pET17b plasmid vector (Novagen, Madison,
Wis.) previously cut with <italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII or <italic>Eco</italic>RI
and dephosphorylated. The ligation mixture was transformed into XL1 Blue
MRF&#x2032; competent cells (Stratagene), and plasmid DNA was prepared for
sequencing (Qiagen Inc., Valencia, Calif.). Recombinant protein was expressed by
transforming plasmid DNA into BL21 pLys S competent cells (Novagen) and inducing
a single-colony cell culture with 2 mM
isopropyl-&#x03B2;-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG; Sigma Chemical Co.).
Full-length antigen was amplified with primers
5&#x2032;-CTAGTT<italic>AGTACT</italic>CAGTCGCAGACCGTG and
3&#x2032;-GCAGTGAC<italic>GAATTC</italic>ACTTCGACTCC by using 200 ng of total genomic
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> Erdman strain DNA and Accuzyme (Intermountain
Scientific Corporation, Inc., Kaysville, Utah) polymerase. The PCR product was
digested with <italic>Sca</italic>I and <italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into a pET28 vector
modified to include an in-frame methionine and a 6-histidine tag at the amino
terminus. The full-length construct was sequenced and transformed into the
HMS174 pLys S cell line (Novagen), and a single-colony culture was induced with
IPTG. Cultures were disrupted by sonication and recombinant protein was
recovered from cell lysate with an Ni-nitrilotriacetic acid agarose matrix
(Qiagen Inc.). Purified protein was then passed over a Q anion-exchange column
(rXP-1 and rMTB48) (Bio-Rad, Hercules, Calif.), following the manufacturer's
instructions, and was finally dialyzed in 10 mM Tris (pH 8.0). Recombinant
proteins were quality checked for purity by sodium dodecyl sulfate
(SDS)-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE), followed by staining with
Coomassie blue stain and N-terminal protein sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B26">26</xref>), and were quantified by a Micro BCA assay (Pierce,
Rockford, Ill.). Recombinants were assayed for endotoxin contamination by the
<italic>Limulus</italic> assay (Bio Whittaker, Walkersville,
Md.).</p></sec><sec><title>Rabbit antiserum.</title><p>Rabbit antiserum to
recombinant antigens was prepared by injecting 200 &#x03BC;g of protein in 1 ml
of incomplete Freund's adjuvant (IFA; Sigma Chemical Co.) and 100 &#x03BC;g of
muramyl dipeptide subcutanously. Six weeks later, the animals were boosted with
100 &#x03BC;g of protein in IFA, followed by a final boost with 50 &#x03BC;g
administered intravenously 1 month later. Animals were killed 1 week after the
final boost, and sera were stored in aliquots at
&#x2212;20&#x00B0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Study population.</title><p>Serum
samples were obtained from individuals who had pulmonary tuberculosis alone
prior to treatment (culture and/or acid-fast bacillus smear positive) or who had
documented coinfections with HIV, as evidenced by a positive HIV type 1- and HIV
type 2-specific antibody ELISA. These included samples from Brazil (Roberto
Badaro, Federal University of Bahia, Salvador, Brazil), Uganda and South Africa
(Milton Tam, Program for Appropriate Technology in Health, Seattle, Wash.), and
the Philippines (Babi Tan, American Leprosy Foundation, Cebu City, Philippines)
and sera from patients with tuberculosis (Nevin Turgay, Bornova-Izmir, Turkey).
Samples from patients with lung cancer and pneumonia (China) were obtained from
Robert Cole (ICT Diagnostics, Frenchs Forest, Australia). To further evaluate
the specificity of the MTB48 antigen, we obtained sera from individuals who were
purified protein derivative (PPD) positive (induration, &#x003E;10 mm) (culture,
clinically, and radiographically negative for tuberculosis) and individuals who
were PPD negative (King County Tuberculosis Clinic, Seattle, Wash.). Sera from
healthy blood donors (from the United States) were obtained from Boston
Biomedica (West Bridgewater, Mass.), and sera from individuals who were HIV
seropositive alone were obtained from Robert Ackridge (Fred Hutchinson Cancer
Research Institute, Seattle, Wash.).</p></sec><sec><title>Southern blot
analysis.</title><p>Genomic DNA was prepared by standard techniques and digested
with <italic>Pst</italic>I (Gibco BRL). One microgram of each digest was run on a
1.0&#x0025; agarose gel and stained with ethidium bromide to confirm the
equivalent loading of each lane prior to overnight transfer to a Nytran nylon
membrane (Schleicher &#x0026; Schuell). Insert DNA isolated by gel
electrophoresis was labeled by random hexamer primer extension with
&#x005B;<sup>32</sup>P&#x005D;dCTP and hybridized with blots overnight at
65&#x00B0;C. Blots were washed at 65&#x00B0;C twice for 15 min each time with
2&#x00D7; SSC (1&#x00D7; SSC is 0.15 M NaCl plus 0.015 M sodium citrate) and
0.1&#x00D7; SSC containing 0.1&#x0025; SDS and exposed to X-ray film (Kodak,
XAR-5).</p></sec><sec><title>Western blot analysis.</title><p>Recombinant
antigens and native <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> proteins were subjected to SDS-PAGE
analysis with 15&#x0025; polyacrylamide minigels. A total of 200 ng of rMTB48
per lane was used for screening of patient serum by Western blot analysis.
Cellular localization of native protein was determined by loading 10 &#x03BC;g
of an <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cytoplasm preparation; 2.5 &#x03BC;g each of
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cell membrane fraction, cell wall fraction, and CFPs
(provided by John Belisle, Colorado State University, produced through National
Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases-National Institutes of Health
Tuberculosis Research Materials contract N01-AI-25147); and 25 ng of recombinant
protein. The proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose (BA-85; Schleicher
&#x0026; Schuell) and blocked for 1 h at room temperature with
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing 1&#x0025; Tween 20. The blots were
then washed three times for 10 min each time in PBS containing 0.1&#x0025; Tween
20 and 0.5 M sodium chloride (wash buffer). Next, the blots were probed for 1 h
at room temperature with serum diluted 1:500 in wash buffer, followed by three
washes (10 min each time) in wash buffer. The blots were then incubated for 45
min at room temperature with protein A-horseradish peroxidase diluted 1:20,000
in wash buffer and again washed three times (10 min each time) in wash buffer.
Finally, the blots were incubated in chemiluminescent substrate (ECL; Amersham
Plc, Little Charlton, United Kingdom) for &#x2248;1 min and were then exposed to
X-ray film (XAR5) for 10 to 60 s, as required. The integrity of the protein in
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cellular protein fractions was confirmed by probing a
Western blot with a rabbit antitubulin
antiserum.</p></sec><sec><title>ELISA.</title><p>Ninety-six-well microtiter
plates (Corning Costar, Cambridge, Mass.) were coated overnight at 4&#x00B0;C
with recombinant proteins (200 ng/well). The plates were then aspirated and
blocked with PBS containing 1&#x0025; (wt/vol) bovine serum albumin for 2 h at
room temperature. This was followed by washing in PBS containing 0.1&#x0025;
Tween 20 (PBST). A dilution of serum (1/100) in PBS containing 0.1&#x0025;
bovine serum albumin was added to the wells, and the plates were incubated for
30 min at room temperature, followed by washing six times with PBST and then
incubation with protein A-horseradish peroxidase conjugate (1/20,000 dilution;
Sigma Chemical Co.) for 30 min. The plates were then washed six times in PBST
and were then incubated with tetramethylbenzidine substrate (Kirkegaard &#x0026;
Perry Laboratories, Inc., Gaithersburg, Md.) for 15 min. The reaction was
stopped by the addition of 1 N sulfuric acid, and the plates were read at 450 nm
with an ELISA plate reader (EL311; Biotek Instruments, Hyland Park, Va.). The
cutoff for the assays was determined from the mean for the negative population
plus 3 standard deviations of the mean. For the data in Table <xref
ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, the signal-to-cutoff ratio was determined by
dividing the sample ELISA value by the cutoff value.</p><table-wrap
id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of the seroreactivities of
recombinant proteins TbH4 and XP-1 with full-length
MTB48</p></caption><table><tr><th rowspan="3">Patient identification</th><th
colspan="2">ELISA result<xref ref-type="table-fn"
rid="TF1-A"></xref></th></tr><tr><td
colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><th>rXP-1</th><th>rTbH4</th><th>rMTB48</th></tr>
<tr><td
colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>383004</td><td>0.956</td><td><bold>1.942</bold></td
><td><bold>2.349</bold></td></tr><tr><td>392004</td><td><bold>7.446</bold></td><td><bold>4.375
</bold></td><td><bold>5.287</bold></td></tr><tr><td>393004</td><td><bold>1.515</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>3.994</bold></td><td><bold>4.379</bold></td></tr><tr><td>395004</td><td><bold>2.392</bold></td
><td><bold>1.494</bold></td><td><bold>1.591</bold></td></tr><tr><td>396004</td><td>0.621</td
><td><bold>1.990</bold></td><td><bold>2.158</bold></td></tr><tr><td>398004</td><td>0.902</td
><td><bold>1.737</bold></td><td><bold>2.241</bold></td></tr><tr><td>407004</td><td><bold>1.201
</bold></td><td><bold>1.625</bold></td><td><bold>2.145</bold></td></tr><tr><td>416004</td><td>0.
830</td><td><bold>1.628</bold></td><td><bold>1.917</bold></td></tr><tr><td>445004</td>
<td><bold>3.642</bold></td><td><bold>3.387</bold></td><td><bold>4.076</bold></td></tr><tr><td>454004</td
><td><bold>1.070</bold></td><td><bold>1.085</bold></td><td><bold>1.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td>
465004</td><td>0.856</td><td><bold>2.431</bold></td><td><bold>2.796</bold></td></tr><tr><td>
470004</td><td><bold>1.595</bold></td><td><bold>2.795</bold></td><td><bold>3.455</bold></td></tr>
<tr><td>476004</td><td><bold>1.204</bold></td><td><bold>3.117</bold></td><td><bold>3.662</bold></td
></tr><tr><td>482004</td><td><bold>2.119</bold></td><td><bold>4.313</bold></td><td><bold>4.386
</bold></td></tr><tr><td>487004</td><td>0.626</td><td><bold>1.795</bold></td><td><bold>2.080
</bold></td></tr><tr><td>489004</td><td><bold>2.667</bold></td><td><bold>4.578</bold>
</td><td><bold>4.405</bold></td></tr><tr><td>490004</td><td>0.502</td>
<td><bold>1.613</bold></td><td><bold>1.491</bold></td></tr><tr><td>506004</td>
<td>0.452</td><td><bold>1.444</bold></td><td><bold>1.524</bold></td></tr><tr><td>514004</td><td><bold>2.720</bold></td><td><bold>4.778</bold></td
><td><bold>4.881</bold></td></tr></table><table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="TF1-A">
<p>Data are
normalized to a cutoff value (based on the mean plus 3 standard deviations) of
1.0 to allow comparison among groups. Positive results are shown in boldface
type.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec><title>Nucleotide sequence accession
number.</title><p>The GenBank accession number for <italic>mtb48</italic> is <ext-link
ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="AY029285"/>.</p></sec></sec><sec
sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Expression cloning and molecular
characterization of <italic>mtb48</italic></title><p>Two genomic expression libraries,
constructed with randomly sheared <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> Erdman strain and
H37Rv strain genomic DNA, were screened with two pools of patient sera. The
first pool consisted of sera from five patients with extrapulmonary disease
(Erdman library), and the second pool consisted of sera from three patients
whose sera were strongly reactive with the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> lysate
(H37Rv library). These screenings resulted in the cloning of <italic>mtb48</italic> in
two sections (clone <italic>tbh4</italic> from the H37Rv library and clone <italic>xp-1</italic>
from the Erdman library) that overlap with 100&#x0025; identity by 1,041 bp
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Clone <italic>tbh4</italic> contains the
amino-terminal 1,319 bp, while clone <italic>xp-1</italic> contains the carboxy 1,101-bp
terminus of a 1,380-bp ORF. The cloned inserts contain a predicted
ribosome-binding site (Shine-Dalgarno sequence; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F1">1</xref>) 17 bp upstream from the predicted ATG start codon and an ORF
that represents a predicted polypeptide of 47.6 kDa. The predicted polypeptide
contains no hydrophobic leader sequence, nor does it contain predicted
transmembrane domains, as determined by the PSORT program. However, analysis of
hydrophilicity indicates three hydrophobic stretches in the carboxy-terminal
half of the polypeptide that could serve as transmembrane regions (Fig. <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="F1"><label>Figure
1</label><caption><p>Relationship of full-length MTB48 to partial ORFs from
genomic clones <italic>tbh4</italic> and <italic>xp-1</italic>. Partial ORFs for TbH4 (upper
line in the underlines) and XP-1 (lower line in the underlines) are underlined,
and a double line indicates their overlap. The indicated polypeptide sequences
were used to develop constructs for rTbH4, rXP-1, and rMTB48 protein expression.
A potential ribosome-binding site (RB) is indicated by a thick bar, and the
predicted ATG initiation codon is shown in bold and underlined. The nucleotide
sequence number is shown on the right.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jm0711513001"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><fig id="F2"><label>Figure
2</label><caption><p>Protein sequence analysis of MTB48 including hydrophilicity
(A), antigenic index (B), and surface probability (C). Analysis was performed
with DNA Star protein analysis software (Protean 4.0) by using the
Kyte-Doolittle hydrophilicity plot, the Jameson-Wolf antigenic index, and the
Emini surface probability plot. A thick bar indicates a region proposed to be
cleaved from the native protein to allow release from the cell. Protein amino
acid numbers are shown above and below the plots, while the relative peak
heights are shown to the left.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jm0711513002"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>Genomic organization of
<italic>mtb48</italic></title><p>Database searches with the nucleotide and predicted
protein sequences for <italic>mtb48</italic> resulted in a 100&#x0025; match with <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv genomic DNA (GenBank accession number <ext-link
ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="AL022120"/>) and hypothetical protein Rv3881c (GenBank accession
number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="G70803"/>), a 99&#x0025; match with <italic>M. bovis</italic> (GenBank
accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="U34848"/>) and <italic>M.
bovis</italic> BCG (GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="U35019"/>) strain DNA,
and a 98.7&#x0025; match with the <italic>M. bovis</italic> and <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG
predicted protein sequences. Of interest, a partial genomic sequence (GenBank
accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="AF001303"/>) from an
Indian <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> clinical isolate (isolate NTI 64719) shows at
least 98.8 to 99.6&#x0025; identity to the <italic>mtb48</italic> sequence, given the
degenerate bases contained in this sequence. Together, this information
indicates that the <italic>mtb48</italic> sequence is well conserved between species
(<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. bovis</italic>) and between geographically
isolated strains from the United States and India. The genomic location of
<italic>mtb48</italic> is 826 bp upstream from a 9,504-bp sequence (which contains the
<italic>esat-6</italic> &#x005B;accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="U34848"/>&#x005D; gene)
that is deleted in the BCG strain of <italic>M. bovis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B24">24</xref>). Southern blot analysis was performed with genomic DNA from
both clinical and environmental <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> isolates. An
<italic>mtb48</italic>-specific probe hybridized to 5.5-kbp reactive <italic>Pst</italic>I
fragments in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> isolates, including strains H37Ra, H37Rv,
Erdman (data not shown), and C (data not shown), and to a 6.5-kbp fragment in
the <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG isolate (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).
No reactivity was seen with <italic>M. leprae, M. smegmatis, Mycobacterium vaccae,
M. gordonae, Mycobacterium chelonae, M. fortuitum, M. scrofulaceum</italic>, or
<italic>M. avium</italic>. The <italic>Pst</italic>I fragments correspond in size to those of
the fragments predicted from the genomic DNA sequence. The difference in
fragment size between <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> isolates and the <italic>M.
bovis</italic> BCG isolate can be attributed to a deletion event in BCG which
removes the <italic>Pst</italic>I site that is found in the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
isolates.</p><fig id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Southern blot
analysis of <italic>mtb48</italic> showing hybridization of a labeled <italic>tbh4</italic>
nucleotide probe with <italic>Pst</italic>I-digested genomic DNA from the <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG isolates tested but not from <italic>M.
leprae</italic> or the environmental mycobacteria tested. Arrows indicate the
migration of a labeled 6.5-kbp fragment from the BCG strain of <italic>M. bovis</italic>
(top arrow) and 5.5-kbp DNA fragments from <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> isolates
(bottom arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="jm0711513003"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>Recombinant protein
expression and purification.</title><p>Four recombinant proteins representing
the amino (rTbH4) and caroxy (rXP-1) termini and the full-length sequence
(rMTB48) for MTB48 and the mature polypeptide for the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
38-kDa antigen (r38 kDa) were overexpressed and purified by using a 6-histidine
tag and metal affinity chromatography. Recombinant constructs were 1,341, 1,125,
1,404, and 1,080 bp, including the ATG start codon, 6-histidine tag, and stop
codon, for rTbH4, rXP-1, rMTB48, and the 38-kDa antigen, respectively, and
expressed recombinant proteins were 46.0, 38.6, 48.6, and 36.8 kDa for rTbH4,
rXP-1, rMTB48, and the 38-kDa antigen, respectively. All recombinant proteins
were tested for purity by N-terminal sequencing, Western blotting, and Coomassie
blue staining and were determined to be over 95&#x0025;
pure.</p></sec><sec><title>Western blot analysis.</title><p>The cellular
localization of native protein was determined by probing a Western blot with
rabbit rMTB48 antiserum. The blot contained fractionated <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> proteins, including cytoplasmic, membrane, and cell wall
fractions; CFPs; and rMTB48. Two major bands of approximately equal reactivity
at 43 and 55 kDa were seen in the cytoplasmic fraction, while bands with little
or no reactivity were observed in the membrane or cell wall fractions. A single
band of 43 kDa was seen in the CFP lane, while two bands of 38 and 55 kDa were
seen in the recombinant protein lane (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F4">4</xref>). The 43-kDa form found in the CFP fraction appears to be
identical in size to the 43-kDa truncated or processed form of MTB48 seen in the
cytoplasmic fraction. Both the cytoplasmic native protein and the recombinant
protein each show a processed form, with the said forms being of approximately
equal molar concentrations, indicating that the two proteins might be processed
by the same or a similar process.</p><fig id="F4"><label>Figure
4</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis indicates that the cellular
localization of native MTB48 protein is in the cytoplasm and the culture
filtrate (CFP). Ten micrograms of an <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cytoplasm
preparation, 2.5 &#x03BC;g each of cell membrane, cell wall, and CFPs, and 25 ng
of recombinant MTB48 were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose,
and probed with an MTB48 rabbit polyclonal antibody. A 55-kDa band (top arrow)
is seen in both the cytoplasm and the recombinant protein lanes, while a 43-kDa
band (middle arrow) is seen in both the cytoplasm and the CFP lanes. A second
band of reactivity at approximately 38 kDa is shown in the recombinant protein
lane (bottom arrow).</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jm0711513004"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>ELISA evaluation of
recombinant proteins XP-1, TbH4, and MTB48.</title><p>Nineteen MTB48-positive
patient serum samples were assayed with rXP-1 and rTbH4 to determine the general
location of antigenic epitopes on rMTB48 (Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>). rTbH4 was reactive with 19 of 19 serum samples, while rXP-1
was reactive with 11 of 19 serum samples. These data indicate that approximately
42&#x0025; of MTB48-positive patient serum samples are reactive only with an
amino-terminal epitope(s), while 58&#x0025; of the serum samples are reactive
with a central epitope(s) and, potentially, an additional amino-terminal
epitope(s).</p></sec><sec><title>ELISA evaluation of sera from patients with
tuberculosis and controls.</title><p>Sera from individuals with tuberculosis in
the presence or absence of HIV infection, PPD-positive individuals with no
evidence of disease, and PPD-negative individuals were tested by ELISA with
tuberculosis lysate, r38 kDa, and rMTB48 (Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T2">2</xref>). The sensitivities of recombinant proteins with serum samples
from HIV-infected individuals in Africa with <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
coinfections were 44.4 and 66.7&#x0025; for rMTB48 and r38 kDa, respectively.
The sensitivity of rMTB48 and r38 kDa used in combination was 74.1&#x0025; (a
gain of 7.4&#x0025; over that obtained with r38 kDa only), indicating that the
reactivities of the two recombinant antigens were complementary. Overall
sensitivities for patients with only <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infection were
29.8 and 43.4&#x0025; for rMTB48 and r38 kDa, respectively. The sensitivity for
the antigens used in combination, however, was 56.3&#x0025;, indicating a
greater contribution (a gain of 12.9&#x0025;) of rMTB48 with these serum
samples. Among the 419 serum samples from patients with only tuberculosis
evaluated by ELISA, rMTB48 was reactive with 32.1&#x0025; of the serum samples
from patients with smear-positive tuberculosis and 17.2&#x0025; of patients with
smear-negative disease; and r38 kDa was reactive with 47 and 23.4&#x0025; of
smear-positive and smear-negative patients, respectively. Comparison of the
ELISA values for serum samples from <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected patients
in Brazil and Africa (smear positive) shows a similar sensitivity. rMTB48
detected <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> in 32.7&#x0025; of the Brazilian samples and
30.3&#x0025; of the African samples, while r38 kDa detected <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> in 48.4 and 40.9&#x0025; of these samples, respectively. Also,
the gain in sensitivity with rMTB48 over that with r38 kDa was similar for both:
13.7 versus 12.1&#x0025;, respectively. The specificities for rMTB48 and r38
kDa, including all control sera, were 97.8 and 96.1&#x0025;, respectively, while
the specificity for rMTB48 and r38 kDa in combination was 94&#x0025;. No
antibody reactivity with rMTB48 was seen for sera from the non-<italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic>-infected control groups, including sera from HIV-positive
patients, lung cancer patients, and pneumonia patients. Specificities of 98.2
and 93.1&#x0025; were determined for MTB48 with class II (PPD positive) and
class 0/I (PPD negative) <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected sera, respectively.
ELISA results for a subset of 248 smear-positive and 52 smear-negative Brazilian
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> patient serum samples are displayed graphically in Fig.
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. Taken together, these data indicate that
rMTB48 adds to the sensitivity of a 38-kDa antigen-based serological test for
<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> in a variety of diverse clinical and geographic
settings.</p><table-wrap id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>ELISA reactivities
of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> lysate, rMTB48, and r38 kDa with HIV-positive and
-negative sera from patients with tuberculosis and controls<xref
ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-A"></xref></p></caption><table><tr><th
rowspan="3">Serum group and patient status</th><th rowspan="3">Origin</th><th
rowspan="3">No. of serum samples</th><th rowspan="3">HIV status</th><th
rowspan="3">Smear result</th><th colspan="4">No. of samples positive by
ELISA</th></tr><tr><td
colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><th>Lysate</th><th>MTB48</th><th>38
kDa</th><th>38 kDa &#x002B; MTB48 </th></tr><tr><td
colspan="9"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Sera from patients
with:</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;TB,<xref
ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-B"></xref> HIV, and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
coinfection</td><td
align="left">Uganda</td><td>17</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>7</td>
<td>8</td><td>12</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left">Uganda</td><td>2<xref ref-type="table-fn"
rid="TF2-C"></xref></td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
<td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">South
Africa</td><td>8</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>5
</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Total</td><td
align="left"/><td>27</td><td/><td/><td>14</td><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>20</td>
</tr><tr><td>&#x2003;TB</td><td
align="left">Brazil</td><td>248</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>165
</td><td>81</td><td>120</td><td>154</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left"/><td>52</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>24</td><td>9</td>
<td>11</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left">Uganda</td><td>15</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>10</td>
<td>10</td><td>12</td><td>12 </td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">South
Africa</td><td>51</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>47</td><td>10</td>
<td>15</td><td>23</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left">Turkey</td><td>11</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>8</td>
<td>3</td><td>9</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left">Philippines</td><td>31</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td>24
</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td/><td
align="left"/><td>11</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td>7</td><td>2</td>
<td>4</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Total</td><td
align="left"/><td>419</td><td/><td/><td>285</td><td>125</td><td>182</td><td>236
</td></tr><tr><td>Control sera</td><td
align="left"/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;HIV
infection</td><td align="left">United
States</td><td>11</td><td>&#x002B;</td><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Class II TB (PPD positive)</td><td
align="left">Africa</td><td>3</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>
0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Europe<xref ref-type="table-fn"
rid="TF2-D"></xref></td><td>6</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>
0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Southeast
Asia</td><td>7</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>2</td
></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">United States-Latin
America</td><td>41</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>4</td><td>1</td><td>3</td><td>4
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Total</td><td
align="left"/><td>57</td><td/><td/><td>6</td><td>1</td><td>5</td><td>6</td></tr>
<tr><td>&#x2003;Class 0/I TB (PPD negative)</td><td
align="left">Africa</td><td>1</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>
0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Europe<xref ref-type="table-fn"
rid="TF2-D"></xref></td><td>3</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>
0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Southeast
Asia</td><td>3</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td
></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">United States-Latin
America</td><td>22</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>3
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Total</td><td
align="left"/><td>29</td><td/><td/><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>3</td></tr>
<tr><td>&#x2003;Other</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;&#x2003;Lung cancer</td><td
align="left">China</td><td>13</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>
0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;&#x2003;Pneumonia</td><td
align="left">China</td><td>18</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>5</td><td>0</td><td>
1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;&#x2003;Healthy controls</td><td
align="left">China
(Caucasian)</td><td>9</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>0</td>
<td>0 </td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">United
States</td><td>95</td><td>&#x2212;</td><td/><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>4
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x2003;Total</td><td
align="left"/><td>135</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>5</td>
</tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2-A"><p>Control sera were from HIV-positive,
PPD-positive, and PPD-negative individuals, healthy controls, and patients with
lung cancer and pneumonia.</p></fn><fn id="TF2-B"><p>TB,
tuberculosis.</p></fn><fn id="TF2-C"><p>One individual was positive for
tuberculosis by X ray.</p></fn><fn id="TF2-D"><p>Primarily from Russia and its
satellite regions where tuberculosis is endemic.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig
id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Distribution of MTB48 ELISA
reactivity among sera from healthy blood donors (<italic>n</italic> = 95), PPD-positive
individuals (<italic>n</italic> = 57), PPD-negative individuals (<italic>n</italic> = 29), and
Brazilian tuberculosis patients who were smear (acid-fast bacillus
&#x005B;AFB&#x005D;) positive (<italic>n</italic> = 248) and negative (<italic>n</italic> = 52).
The assay cutoff value (horizontal bar) was determined from the mean for the
healthy donor population plus 3 standard deviations of the mean. OD 450, optical
density at 450 nm.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jm0711513005"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec
sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The development of a serodiagnostic
assay for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> with high degrees of sensitivity and
specificity will most likely require a panel of several recombinant antigens or
a fusion polyprotein that comprises the critical epitopes. This is due to the
highly heterogeneous nature of antigen recognition by infected individuals that
results, in part, from diverse genetic backgrounds, exposure to different
stage-specific or strain-specific antigens, bacillary loads, patient health, and
individual treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Data
presented in this report indicate that MTB48 is an important component of the
antigen cocktail that will be required for diagnostic assay development. MTB48,
which was cloned from both the Erdman and the H37Rv strains of <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic> by serological expression screening with <italic>M.
tuberculosis</italic>-infected patient serum, encodes a predicted 47.6-kDa
polypeptide (approximately 54 kDa under reducing conditions, possibly due to the
high proline content &#x005B;7.6&#x0025;&#x005D;) with no known function and is
restricted to virulent and avirulent strains of the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
complex and <italic>M. bovis. mtb48</italic> genomic nucleotide sequences from the
Erdman (clone <italic>xp-1</italic>) and H37Rv strains (clone <italic>tbh4</italic>) were
identical, and database searches showed that the <italic>mtb48</italic> genomic sequence
(Erdman strain) was identical to the H37Rv genomic sequence (GenBank accession
number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="AL022120"/>) and 99&#x0025; identical to the corresponding <italic>M.
bovis</italic> sequence (GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="U34848"/>). A partial
genomic sequence from an <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> clinical isolate from India
(GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="AF001303"/>) also shows
approximately 99&#x0025; identity to <italic>mtb48</italic>. Taken together, this
information indicates that the <italic>mtb48</italic> sequence is well conserved between
species and between geographically isolated strains from the United States and
India. The native MTB48 protein is cytoplasmic and appears to be cleaved near
the carboxy terminus to form a 43-kDa protein that is then shed. One cannot rule
out the possibility, however, that in the culture filtrate the protein is
degraded to the smaller fragment by secreted or shed proteases. The
carboxy-terminal segment contains hydrophobic regions that could be removed upon
processing, thus allowing secretion or shedding of the antigen. Preliminary
epitope mapping shows that of the MTB48-positive patient serum samples tested,
42&#x0025; recognize an amino-terminal epitope(s), which is missing in rXP-1,
while 58&#x0025; recognize one or more central epitopes, indicating the
possibility of several B-cell epitopes along the molecule. Protein analysis
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) shows that the amino terminus and
central region of the protein are hydrophilic and are predicted to be highly
antigenic. Surface probability predictions also indicate clusters of
surface-exposed regions in the amino-terminal region and in the midregion of the
molecule.</p><p>The serodiagnostic potential of rMTB48 compared to that of r38
kDa was evaluated by ELISA. The 38-kDa <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> antigen was
chosen for comparison because of its relatively high degrees of sensitivity and
specificity, as determined in numerous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B34">34</xref>). Serological sensitivity for the 38-kDa antigen ranges from
16 to 89&#x0025;, and specificity ranges from 93 to 100&#x0025; (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>, <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>), depending largely upon the selection of
patient populations in each study. In the present study, overall sensitivity
values for rMTB48 and r38 kDa, including those for samples from patients with
HIV coinfection and smear-positive and -negative patients, were 30.7 and
44.8&#x0025;, respectively, with a sensitivity of 57.4&#x0025; when both
antigens were used in combination. Samples from patients with HIV coinfection
alone resulted in higher values (44.4, 66.7, and 74.1&#x0025;, respectively), as
did samples from smear-positive patients (32.1, 47, and 60.6&#x0025;,
respectively). Values for samples from smear-negative patients were 17.2, 23.4,
and 32.8&#x0025;, respectively. Thus, MTB48 is a highly conserved antigen and
its serological reactivity complements that of the 38-kDa antigen in the
detection of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infection.</p><p>Although rMTB48 adds to
the overall sensitivity of the 38-kDa antigen, an <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
serodiagnostic reagent with high degrees of sensitivity and specificity will
depend on the use of several antigens, including r38 kDa and rMTB48. Detection
of problematic infections, such as smear-negative infections, depends on a
combination of techniques, including serology, detection of clinical symptoms,
and radiography. Additional effort must be directed toward the serological
detection of smear-negative infections. Although patients with smear-negative
infections are less infectious and have a lower mortality rate than patients
with smear-positive infections, the number of patients with smear-negative
infections is estimated to exceed the number of patients with smear-positive
infections, and over half of the patients with smear-negative infections will
progress to active disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). In
addition, coinfections with HIV have disproportionately increased the number of
smear-negative cases. Our studies continue to be directed toward the development
of a rapid serodiagnostic assay that uses an optimized set of recombinant
antigens that will be expressed as one or more fusion
polyproteins.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank
Thomas Vedvick and Darrick Carter for protein sequence data, Dan Hoppe and Joe
Parsons for assistance with DNA sequencing, and Stephan Johnson and Rhea Coler
for providing genomic DNA for Southern blot analysis. We also thank Jonathan
Clapper for performing lipopolysaccharide assays with purified recombinant
antigens and John Belisle, who provided fractionated <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>
cellular proteins (Tuberculosis Research Materials contract N01-AI-25147). We
also acknowledge Robert Akridge (Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Institute) for
providing the serum samples from U.S. HIV-positive patients and Charles Nolan at
the King County Tuberculosis Clinic for providing PPD-positive and -negative
samples.</p><p>M.J.L. and D.C.D. contributed equally to the data presented in
this report.</p><p>This work was partially supported by NIH grants AI-39879 (to
R.L.H.) and AI-44373 (to
S.G.R.).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref
id="B1"><label>1</label><citation><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>A.
B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>E.
B.</given-names></name><article-title>Structure and mapping of antigenic domains of protein
antigen b, a 38,000-molecular-weight protein of <italic>Mycobacterium
tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>Infect.
Immun.</source><volume>57</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>2481</fpage><lpage>
2488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2545626</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B2"><label>2</label><citation><name><surname>Ashbridge</surname><given-names>K.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestidge</surname><given-names>R.
L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>R.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><article-title>The
mapping of an antibody-binding region on the Mycobacterium tuberculosis 19
kilodalton antigen.</article-title><source>J.
Immunol.</source><volume>144</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>3137</fpage><lpage>
3142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1691228</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B3"><label>3</label><citation><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>S.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>M.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>H.
G.</given-names></name><article-title>Respiratory infections in immunocompromised
patients.</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Pulm.
Med.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>173
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228742</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B4"><label>4</label><citation><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>J.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuoh</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>G.
L.</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical evaluation of the enhanced Gen-Probe Amplified
Mycobacterium Tuberculosis Direct Test for rapid diagnosis of tuberculosis in
prison inmates.</article-title><source>J. Clin.
Microbiol.</source><volume>37</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage
>1425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10203498</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B5"><label>5</label><citation><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>E.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heifets</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iseman
</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><article-title>Immunologic diagnosis of tuberculosis: a
review.</article-title><source>Tuber. Lung
Dis.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10970761</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B6"><label>6</label><citation><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Emerging infectious diseases and pathogens.</article-title><source>Nurs. Clin.
N.
Am.</source><volume>34</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>442
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10318733</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B7"><label>7</label><citation><name><surname>Colebunders</surname><given-names>R.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><article-title>A review of the
diagnosis and treatment of smear-negative pulmonary
tuberculosis.</article-title><source>Int. J. Tuberc. Lung
Dis.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>107
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10694086</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B8"><label>8</label><citation><name><surname>Demkow</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>T.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strzalkowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Michalowska-Mitczuk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustynowicz-Kopec
</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialas-Chromiec</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skopinska-Rozewska</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwolska</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><article-title>
Diagnostic value of IgG antibody levels against 38 kDa mycobacterial
antigen.</article-title><source>Pneumonol. Alergol.
Pol.</source><volume>66</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>516
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10391957</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B9"><label>9</label><citation><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>D.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderson</surname><given-names>M.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>C.
H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bement</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos-
Neto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skeiky</surname><given-names>Y. A.
W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedvick</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badaro
</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>S.
G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular
and immunological characterization of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>
CFP-10, an immunodiagnostic antigen missing in <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic>
BCG.</article-title><source>J. Clin.
Microbiol.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>3285</fpage><lpage
>3290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10970372</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B10"><label>10</label><citation><name><surname>Eltringham</surname><given-names>I.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drobniewski</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><article-title>
Multiple drug resistant tuberculosis: aetiology, diagnosis and
outcome.</article-title><source>Br. Med.
Bull.</source><volume>54</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>578
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10326285</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B11"><label>11</label><citation><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><article-title>Tuberculosis and
radiologic diagnosis 100 years after W.C.
Roentgen.</article-title><source>Pneumologie</source><volume>49</volume><year>1995
</year><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>662</lpage>.<pub-id
pub-id-type="pmid">8577672</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B12"><label>12</label><citation><name><surname>Foulds</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name
><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><article-title>New tools for the
diagnosis of tuberculosis: the perspective of developing
countries.</article-title><source>Int. J. Tuberc. Lung
Dis.</source><volume>2</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>783
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9783521</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B13"><label>13</label><citation><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Molecular techniques for the diagnosis of respiratory bacterial
infection.</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Pulm.
Med.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>178
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228743</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B14"><label>14</label><citation><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>A.
M.</given-names></name><article-title>The tuberculosis epidemic. Scientific challenges and
opportunities.</article-title><source>Public Health
Rep.</source><volume>113</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>136
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9719813</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B15"><label>15</label><citation><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>J.
R.</given-names></name><article-title>Resurgence of tuberculosis and the impact of HIV
infection.</article-title><source>Br. Med.
Bull.</source><volume>54</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>593
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10326286</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B16"><label>16</label><citation><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>K.
K.</given-names></name><article-title>Serodiagnosis of tuberculosis.</article-title><source>J.
Commun.
Dis.</source><volume>27</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8866984</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B17"><label>17</label><citation><name><surname>Hageman</surname><given-names>J.
R.</given-names></name><article-title>Congenital and perinatal tuberculosis: discussion of
difficult issues in diagnosis and management.</article-title><source>J.
Perinatol.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>
394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766418</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B18"><label>18</label><citation><name><surname>Harboe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Wiker</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><article-title>The 38-kDa protein of
Mycobacterium tuberculosis: a review.</article-title><source>J. Infect.
Dis.</source><volume>166</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>884
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527425</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B19"><label>19</label><citation><name><surname>Harries</surname><given-names>A.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunn</surname
><given-names>P.</given-names></name><article-title>An approach to the problems of diagnosing and
treating adult smear-negative pulmonary tuberculosis in high-HIV-prevalence
settings in sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title><source>Bull. W. H.
O.</source><volume>76</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>662
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10191561</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B20"><label>20</label><citation><name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>R.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglass</surname><given-names>J.
F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>L.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>P.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed
</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>R.
L.</given-names></name><article-title>Mass spectrometric identification of Mtb81, a novel
serological marker for tuberculosis.</article-title><source>J. Clin.
Microbiol.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>2354</fpage><lpage
>2361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835002</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B21"><label>21</label><citation><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>C.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.
L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellner</surname><given-names>J.
J.</given-names></name><article-title>Pulmonary tuberculosis.</article-title><source>Curr. Opin.
Pulm.
Med.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>150
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228738</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B22"><label>22</label><citation><name><surname>Kamholz</surname><given-names>S.
L.</given-names></name><article-title>Resurgence of tuberculosis: the perspective a dozen
years later.</article-title><source>J. Assoc. Acad. Minor
Phys.</source><volume>7</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>86
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8803420</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B23"><label>23</label><citation><name><surname>Lyashchenko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Colangeli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houde</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al
Jahdali</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Gennaro</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><article-title>Heterogeneous antibody
responses in tuberculosis.</article-title><source>Infect.
Immun.</source><volume>66</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>3936</fpage><lpage>
3940</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9673283</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B24"><label>24</label><citation><name><surname>Mahairas</surname><given-names>G.
G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names>P.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>M.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>C.
K.</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular analysis of genetic differences between
<italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG and virulent <italic>M.
bovis</italic>.</article-title><source>J.
Bacteriol.</source><volume>178</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>1274</fpage>
<lpage>1282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631702</pub-id>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B25"><label>25</label><citation><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyashchenko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colangeli</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennaro</surname><given-names>M.
L.</given-names></name><article-title>MTC28, a novel 28-kilodalton proline-rich secreted
antigen specific for the <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>
complex.</article-title><source>Infect.
Immun.</source><volume>65</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>4951</fpage><lpage>
4957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9393781</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B26"><label>26</label><citation><name><surname>Matsudaira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Sequence from picomole quantities of proteins electroblotted onto
polyvinylidene difluoride membranes.</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source><volume>262</volume><year>1987</year><fpage>10035</fpage><lpage>
10038</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3611052</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B27"><label>27</label><citation><name><surname>Migliori</surname><given-names>G.
B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrositti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>
Epidemiology of tuberculosis in Europe.</article-title><source>Monaldi Arch. Chest
Dis.</source><volume>53</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>687
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10063345</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B28"><label>28</label><citation><name><surname>Netto</surname><given-names>E.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raviglione
</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><article-title>Progress in global tuberculosis control
1995&#x2013;1996, with emphasis on 22 high-incidence countries. Global
monitoring and surveillance project.</article-title><source>Int. J. Tuberc. Lung
Dis.</source><volume>3</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>320
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10206501</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B29"><label>29</label><citation><name><surname>Pottumarthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>V.
C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><article-title>A
comparison of seven tests for serological diagnosis of
tuberculosis.</article-title><source>J. Clin.
Microbiol.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>2227</fpage><lpage
>2231</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10834981</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B30"><label>30</label><citation><name><surname>Rattan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N.
</given-names></name><article-title>Multidrug-resistant Mycobacterum tuberculosis: molecular
perspectives.</article-title><source>Emerg. Infect.
Dis.</source><volume>4</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>209
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9621190</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B31"><label>31</label><citation><name><surname>Samanich</surname><given-names>K.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>M.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vissa</surname><given-names>V.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>J.
D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>J.
S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belisle</surname><given-names>J.
T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zolla-Pazner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Laal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><article-title>Serodiagnostic potential of culture
filtrate antigens of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>Clin.
Diagn. Lab.
Immunol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>668
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882669</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B32"><label>32</label><citation><name><surname>Verbon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name
><article-title>Development of a serological test for tuberculosis. Problems and
potential.</article-title><source>Trop. Geogr.
Med.</source><volume>46</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>279
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7855911</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B33"><label>33</label><citation><name><surname>Verbon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Hartskeerl</surname><given-names>R.
A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuitema</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolk
</surname><given-names>A. H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>D.
B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lathigra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><article-title>The
14,000-molecular-weight antigen of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is
related to the alpha-crystallin family of low-molecular-weight heat shock
proteins.</article-title><source>J.
Bacteriol.</source><volume>174</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>1352</fpage>
<lpage>1359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1370952</pub-id>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B34"><label>34</label><citation><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>R.
J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslov</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappuoli
</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>C.
R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vordermeier</surname><given-names>H.
M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasvol
</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Evaluation of the recombinant
38-kilodalton antigen of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> as a potential
immunodiagnostic reagent.</article-title><source>J. Clin.
Microbiol.</source><volume>35</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>
557</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9041387</pub-id> </citation></ref><ref
id="B35"><label>35</label><citation><name><surname>Zumla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Grange</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><article-title>Impact of
HIV infection on tuberculosis.</article-title><source>Postgrad. Med.
J.</source><volume>76</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>268
</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10775277</pub-id>
</citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> <?mtl /hellip?>
