<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../../NCBI/ArchivingDTD/DTD/Working/archivearticle.dtd">
<?mtl hellip?><article>
<!-- Affiliation -->
<front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">mbc</journal-id><journal-id
journal-id-type="pubmed">Mol Biol Cell</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">MOL BIOL
CELL</journal-id><issn>1059-1524</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The American Society for
Cell Biology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<?mtl /hellip?>
<article-meta>
<?mtl hellip?>
<article-id
pub-id-type="publisher-id">1614</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598181</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group><subject>ARTICLE</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic Dynein Light Intermediate Chain Is Required for
Discrete Aspects of Mitosis in <italic>Caenorhabditis
elegans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib
contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>Judith</given-names></name></contrib
></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>John
H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib
contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref
ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN150">&#x002A;</xref></contrib></contrib-group>
<?mtl /hellip?>
<aff id="hhMI">Department of Molecular, Cellular, and Developmental 
Biology, Howard Hughes Medical Institution, University of Colorado, 
Boulder, Colorado 80303-0347</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn id="FN150"><p>Corresponding
author. E-mail address: <email>mhan@colorado.edu</email>.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<?mtl hellip?>
<pub-date
pub-type="pub"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>
12</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2921</fpage><lpage>2933</lpage><history><date
date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2001</year></date><date
date-type="rev-recd"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2001</year></date><date
date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></date>
</history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2001, The American Society for Cell
Biology</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><abstract><p>We describe phenotypic characterization of
<italic>dli-1</italic>, the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> homolog of cytoplasmic
dynein light intermediate chain (LIC), a subunit of the cytoplasmic dynein motor
complex. Animals homozygous for loss-of-function mutations in <italic>dli-1</italic>
exhibit stochastic failed divisions in late larval cell lineages, resulting in
zygotic sterility. <italic>dli-1</italic> is required for dynein function during
mitosis. Depletion of the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene product through RNA-mediated gene
interference (RNAi) reveals an early embryonic requirement. One-cell
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos exhibit failed cell division attempts, resulting
from a variety of mitotic defects. Specifically, pronuclear migration,
centrosome separation, and centrosome association with the male pronuclear
envelope are defective in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. Meiotic spindle
formation, however, is not affected in these embryos. DLI-1, like its vertebrate
homologs, contains a putative nucleotide-binding domain similar to those found
in the ATP-binding cassette transporter family of ATPases as well as other
nucleotide-binding and -hydrolyzing proteins. Amino acid substitutions in a
conserved lysine residue, known to be required for nucleotide binding, confers
complete rescue in a <italic>dli-1</italic> mutant background, indicating this is not an
essential domain for DLI-1 function.</p></abstract>
<?mtl /hellip?>
</article-meta>
<?mtl hellip?></front><body><sec
sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Cytoplasmic dynein is a large
multisubunit complex composed of two motor proteins, the heavy chains, and
several associated subunits that have been named light, light intermediate, and
intermediate chains. These subunits have no sequence homology; instead, the
names reflect their relative molecular weights. Cytoplasmic dynein is the major
microtubule minus-end&#x2013;directed motor protein and has been implicated in a
variety of cellular processes, during both interphase and mitosis. Membranous
vesicle transport, endoplasmic reticulum-to-Golgi transport, and axonal
retrograde transport are all dynein-dependent processes (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B24">Lacey and Haimo, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Dillman
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Presley <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>Dynein's mitotic roles are numerous. Function
blocking antibody experiments against heavy chain in vertebrate cells have shown
the motor protein is required for proper spindle formation and centrosome
separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Vaisberg <italic>et al.</italic>,
1993</xref>). Similar results were observed in <italic>Drosophila</italic> heavy chain
mutants with additional observations suggesting dynein is required to maintain
centrosome association with the nuclear envelope (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B37">Robinson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). In both <italic>Aspergillus
nidulans</italic> and <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>, dynein heavy chain mutations
reveal a role for the complex in nuclear migration (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B31">Plamann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B51">Xiang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). Other recent work suggests dynein
may mediate microtubule binding at the kinetochore (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B48">Wordeman and Mitchison, 1995</xref>).</p><p>The one-cell
<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryo is also an excellent model system for
investigating the roles of dynein, its subunits, and the proteins with which it
interacts. When cytoplasmic dynein heavy chain (<italic>dhc-1</italic>) was eliminated
through RNA-mediated gene interference (RNAi), all of the above-mentioned
phenotypes were observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Pronuclear migration and centrosome separation did not
occur and multiple female pronuclei were formed, suggesting defects in meiosis.
Additionally, centrosomes were dissociated from the male pronuclei in 15&#x0025;
of these embryos.</p><p>The variety of roles dynein plays during mitosis
suggests complex regulation must be at work to ensure proper timing and
coordination with mitotic events. Numerous lines of evidence point to the dynein
subunits as key players in this regulation. For example, the intermediate chain
(IC) subunit has been shown to directly interact with the p150<sup>glued</sup>
subunit of dynactin in vertebrate cell extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B22">Karki and Holzbaur, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B46">Vaughan and Vallee, 1995</xref>). Dynactin is an adapter molecule that
links dynein to vesicular cargo and has been shown to be required for
dynein-dependent vesicle motility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Gill <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1991</xref>). RNAi against the <italic>C. elegans</italic> homologs of
p150<sup>glued</sup> and another dynactin subunit, p50/dynamintin, also revealed
a role in nuclear migration and centrosome separation (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B39">Skop and White, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). IC diversity, as a result of alternative
splicing, gives rise to tissue-specific distribution as well as differential
subcellular localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Nurminsky <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Function blocking antibody experiments directed against
IC suggest it is only required for a subset of dynein functions; spindle
assembly is disrupted as in the dynein heavy chain experiment, but centrosome
separation is not affected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Gaglio <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Additional function blocking experiments against IC
suggest it is also required for proper meiotic spindle formation (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Palazzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Multiple
cytoplasmic dynein light chains have been identified and are also responsible
for linking dynein to specific cargo or regulatory molecules. LC8, for example,
has been shown to be required for proper nuclear migration in <italic>A.
nidulans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Beckwith <italic>et al.</italic>,
1998</xref>). LC8 has also been shown to directly interact with neuronal
nitric-oxide synthase and the Bcl-2 family protein Bim and therefore is
implicated in neurotransmitter function and the apoptotic pathway (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Jaffrey and Snyder, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B35">Puthalakath <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Mutations in another light
chain family member, <italic>roadblock</italic>/LC7, reveal roles in axonal transport
and mitosis in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Bowman <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, the heavy, intermediate, and light
chains all have homologs in axonemal dynein. Light IC (LIC), however, is
specific to cytoplasmic dynein and is the least well characterized subunit of
the complex. No alleles of LIC have previously been described. Recent work has
shown there are two rat light intermediate chains (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B44">Tynan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Each LIC forms a homodimer and
binds the dynein complex mutually exclusive of one another. Additionally, LIC1,
but not LIC2, has been shown to bind pericentrin, a conserved component of the
centrosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Purohit <italic>et al.</italic>,
1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Tynan <italic>et al.</italic>,
2000</xref>). Pericentrin has been observed to translocate along microtubules
toward the centrosomes in a dynein-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B52">Young <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). These data suggest LIC, like the
intermediate and light chains, is responsible for linking dynein to specific
cargo. Recently, antibodies against human LIC were generated and found to
localize to the nuclear periphery and to the microtubule-organizing center in
HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bielli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).
The latter of these observations is consistent with the observed pericentrin
interaction.</p><p>Pepetide sequence analysis of rat LIC revealed no overall
homology to known proteins; however, a putative P-loop sequence was identified
near its N terminus with extended sequence similarity to the ATP-binding
cassette (ABC) transporter family of ATPases (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B15">Gill <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). The P-loop, also known as the Walker A box, is one of three conserved motifs making up the nucleotide-binding
domain found in numerous nucleotide-binding proteins, including ATPases and
kinases, as well as proteins whose functions are not fully understood (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Walker <italic>et al.</italic>, 1982</xref>). LIC, however,
lacks the other two motifs and its ATPase activity has not been
assayed.</p><p>Here, we report the first isolated alleles of dynein LIC and show
it is required for dynein's mitotic roles. Maternal rescue allows
loss-of-function homozygotes to develop to mid-larval stages before cell
division failure begins. However, an early embryonic mitotic requirement is
revealed through RNAi analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials/methods"><title>MATERIALS
AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Strains and Alleles</title><p><italic>C. elegans</italic>
strains were cultured and maintained at 20&#x00B0;C according to standard
procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Brenner, 1974</xref>). Mutagenesis of
wild-type, N2 Bristol animals was performed with 50 mM ethyl methanesulfornate
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Brenner, 1974</xref>). Mutagenized adults were
individually transferred to a Petri plate and allowed to lay eggs. When the F1
progeny had grown to adults (&#x223C;4 d later), 10 F1 animals were randomly
selected and transferred to individual Petri plates. The F2 generation was then
scored under a dissecting microscope for a protruding vulva/sterile phenotype.
Four to five wild-type siblings of these F2 sterile animals were cloned to
obtain heterozygous strains. Approximately 10,000 haploid genome (5000 F1
plates) were screened, and 60 independent strains were isolated. The three
<italic>dli-1</italic> alleles <italic>ku266</italic>, <italic>ku275</italic>, and <italic>ku287</italic> were
isolated in this manner. Each allele was outcrossed at least five times. Mapping
strains used were <italic>unc-30(e191)</italic>, <italic>unc-31(e169) dpy-4(e1166)</italic>, the
deficiency sDf22, and the translocation balancer DnT1 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B36">Riddle <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic
Analysis and Molecular Cloning</title><p><italic>dli-1</italic> was mapped relative to
the cloned markers <italic>unc-31</italic> and <italic>unc-30</italic> on linkage group IV. The
strain <italic>unc-31 dpy-4/ku266</italic> was constructed and a standard three-factor
recombination analysis was performed. Twenty-four recombinants were obtained:
10/12 Dpy-nonUnc and 2/12 Unc-nonDpy recombinants segregated <italic>ku266</italic>. The
deficiency sDf22 was shown to uncover <italic>ku266</italic>, placing the locus left of
the <italic>lev-1</italic> gene. This genetic distance between <italic>unc-31</italic> and
<italic>lev-1</italic> is represented by 12 cosmids interrupted by one sequencing gap
near the <italic>unc-31</italic> locus. Cosmids covering the region between
<italic>unc-31</italic> and <italic>lev-1</italic> were mixed with plasmid DNA carrying the
dominant marker SUR-5::GFP (100 ng/&#x03BC;l) in pools of three (15 ng/&#x03BC;l
each) and injected into the strain <italic>unc-31 ku266/unc-30</italic> (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Mello <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>). SUR-5::GFP served
as a visible transgenic marker for scoring progeny of injected animals. The F1
generation was scored for transgenic fertile animals with the <italic>unc-31</italic>
phenotype to identify rescued homozygous <italic>ku266</italic> animals. The minimal
rescuing subclone pJHY10 of cosmid C39E9 contains 3.5 kb of upstream sequence
and the entire 1.5 kb of coding sequence followed by &#x223C;450 bases of
3&#x2032; untranslated region. This subclone was generated by inserting the
5.5-kb <italic>Xho</italic>I/<italic>Msc</italic>I restriction fragment from C39E9 into the
BlueScript SK<sup>&#x002B;</sup> vector (Stratagene, La Jolla,
CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular Analysis and RNA Interference</title><p>To
identify molecular lesions in the 3 <italic>dli-1</italic> alleles, polymerase chain
reaction of whole-worm lysates was performed (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B3">Barstead <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>), and sequences generated and
compared against wild-type sequence similarly obtained. The <italic>dli-1</italic> cDNAs
yk102f4, yk303f8, and yk448c3 were sequenced with the use of T3- and T7-specific
primers. The three cDNAs were shown to be full length by identification of both
the predicted start and stop codons. Point mutations in the putative P-loop
domain in pJHY10 were generated with the use of the QuickChange site-directed
mutagenesis kit (Stratagene).</p><p>The cDNAs yk102f4 and yk22b3 were used as
templates for generation of double-stranded RNA for <italic>dli-1</italic> and
<italic>dhc-1</italic> RNAi analysis, respectively. yk102f4 is &#x223C;2 kb in length
and encodes a full-length cDNA for <italic>dli-1</italic>. yk22b3 is &#x223C;3 kb and
encodes the 3&#x2032;-most end of <italic>dhc-1</italic>, including part of exon 10 and
the remaining five exons. The methods of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Fire
<italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref> were used for generation and injection of
double-stranded RNA. Double-stranded RNA for <italic>dli-1</italic> and <italic>dhc-1</italic>
were injected at equimolar ratios into either wild-type animals or the
heterozygous strain strain <italic>unc-31 ku266/unc-30</italic> &#x005B;only for
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi)&#x005D;. All cDNAs were provided by Yuji Kohara (National
Institute of Genetics, Mishima, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Video Microscopy
and Immunocytochemistry</title><p>Embryos were dissected from adults in a
minimal volume of M9 buffer with the use of a sterile 20-gauge syringe to cut
the adults open. Embryos were then transferred with a mouth pipette to a
2&#x0025; agar pad on a microscope slide in 5&#x2013;10 &#x03BC;l of M9 buffer
and covered with a coverslip. Time-lapsed movies of one-cell embryos were made
with the use of OpenLab 2.0 software (Improvision, Coventry, United Kingdom),
collecting one Nomarski image per second on a Zeiss Axioskop. These files were
then saved as QuickTime movie files for further analysis. All embryos were
harvested 26&#x2013;30 h after RNAi injections, and all embryos were observed
and movies recorded at 23&#x00B0;C.</p><p>Immunocytochemistry was performed on
single cell embryos harvested as described above. Embryos were placed on subbed
poly-<sc>l</sc>-lysine slides in a minimal volume of M9 buffer and flash frozen
in liquid nitrogen. Embryos were permeabilized with the use of the freeze-crack
method and rehydrated through series of MeOH/phosphate-buffered saline washes
before blocking with goat serum for 0.5 h (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B11">Epstein and Shakes, 1995</xref>). Immunocytochemistry performed on
gonads to visualize sheath cells with the use of antibodies to CEH-18 followed
the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Greenstein <italic>et
al.</italic> (1994)</xref>.</p><p>Primary antibodies were used at the following
concentrations: 1:100 rabbit anti-DHC-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), 1:50 rabbit anti-ZYG-9 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B25">Matthews <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), 1:100 mouse monoclonal
anti-<italic>Drosophila</italic> &#x03B1;-tubulin (4A-1; M. Fuller, Stanford University,
Stanford, CA), and 1:200 anti-CEH-18 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Greenstein
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). Secondary antibodies were used at the following
concentrations: 1:100 tetramethylrhodamine B isothiocyanate-conjugated goat
anti-rabbit and 1:100 Cy-2-conjugated donkey anti-mouse (Jackson Immunoresearch,
West Grove, PA).</p><p>For DNA staining, embryos were incubated for 10 min with
0.1 &#x03BC;g/ml 4&#x2032;,6-diamidino-3-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI).
Embryos were then mounted in &#x223C;10 &#x03BC;l of n-propylgalate (Sigma, St.
Louis, MO) in 80&#x0025; glycerol. Fluorescent images were taken with a Zeiss
Axioskop equipped with a Hamamatsu digital camera and deconvolution was
performed with the use of OpenLab 2.0 software
(Improvision).</p></sec></sec><sec
sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Isolation of dli-1 Alleles and
Molecular Cloning of dli-1</title><p>An ethyl methanesulfornate-induced F1
clonal screen of &#x223C;10,000 haploid genomes was performed to isolate mutants
with a protruding vulva and sterile phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B12">Fay and Han, 2000</xref>; see MATERIALS AND METHODS). Three mutants
with similar vulva phenotypes mapped to the same genetic interval on linkage
group IV between <italic>unc-31</italic> and <italic>dpy-4</italic>. Noncomplementation tests
between these three mutants (<italic>ku266</italic>, <italic>ku275</italic>, and <italic>ku287</italic>)
indicated they are allelic. When <italic>trans</italic> to one another, the various
allelic combinations result in the same protruding vulva and sterile phenotype
seen in the three homozygous mutants. Further mapping with the <italic>ku266</italic>
allele placed it between the cloned genes <italic>unc-31</italic> and <italic>lev-1</italic> in
a region spanned by 12 cosmids (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>;
see MATERIALS AND METHODS).</p><fig id="F1"><caption><p>Map position and genetic structure of <italic>dli-1</italic>. (A)
Top line shows a portion of the genetic map from linkage group IV with relative
positions of relevant genetic markers. Below are the three cosmids injected as a
pool that confer rescue in the <italic>dli-1</italic> alleles. The cosmid C39E9 confers
rescue alone as does the large <italic>Xho</italic>I deletion and the subclone pJHY10.
(B) Structure of the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene showing locations of lesions within the
three alleles and the two splice variants as determined by cDNA sequence
comparison.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="mk1011614001" alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>To identify the
affected locus, germline transformation rescue was performed by injecting pools
of overlapping cosmids from this region into the gonad arms of <italic>ku266</italic>
heterozygotes as described in MATERIALS AND METHODS (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F1">1</xref>A). We were able to rescue both the protruding vulva and
sterile phenotypes with the single cosmid C39E9. A large <italic>Xho</italic>I deletion
of this cosmid (CJHY2), containing only one predicted open reading frame
(C39E9.14), was also able to rescue the phenotypes in all four transgenic lines
obtained, and a minimal rescuing subclone (pJHY10) from the CJHY2 deletion
construct was generated, which contains a 5.5-kb <italic>Xho</italic>I/MscI restriction
fragment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). An NCBI Blast search
with the translation of this predicted open reading frame found homology with
human, rat, and chick LIC with 33&#x0025; sequence identity and 51&#x0025;
sequence similarity throughout the entire lengths of the proteins (Figure <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Two vertebrate LICs have been identified
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Tynan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). LIC1 and
LIC2 are &#x223C;75&#x0025; identical but show mutually exclusive binding to the
dynein motor complex. Additionally, LIC1 specifically binds pericentrin, a
conserved component of the centrosome. C39E9.14 shares the same degree of
similarity with LIC1 and LIC2, and it is the only predicted gene in the <italic>C.
elegans</italic> genome with homology to the LICs; therefore, after <italic>C.
elegans</italic> nomenclature convention, we have given it the name <italic>dli-1</italic>
for cytoplasmic dynein light intermediate chain-1.</p><fig
id="F2"><caption><p>Alignment between DLI-1, rat LIC1,
and human LIC1. Dark shaded boxes show identical residues in two or more of the
three proteins shown. Light gray boxes highlight similar residues. There is
33&#x0025; sequence identity throughout the full length of the proteins and
51&#x0025; similarity. The underlined residues constitute the putative P-loop
sequence and the asterisk highlights the conserved lysine residue that is
mutated in our rescuing constructs to either alanine or asparginine. Sequences
were aligned with the use of Clustal W.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mk1011614002"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>To confirm the mutant phenotypes are the
result of mutations in the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene, the entire <italic>dli-1</italic> open
reading frame was sequenced from the three alleles and compared with wild-type
sequence. Two of the three alleles, <italic>ku266</italic> and <italic>ku275</italic>, result
from premature stop codons in the second and fifth exons, respectively (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B). <italic>ku287</italic> results from a point
mutation in the start codon (ATG to ATA). The next in-frame methionine is found
in the fourth exon. Because the three alleles phenocopy one another, are not
exacerbated when placed in <italic>trans</italic> to a deficiency, and based on the
likely instability of messages produced by the introduction of premature stop
codons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Pulak and Anderson, 1993</xref>), it is
likely all three alleles are strong loss-of-function or null
mutations.</p><p>Sequences of three full-length cDNAs were generated and
compared against one another, revealing two distinct splice variants that differ
only by 6 bp at the beginning of the fifth exon (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F1">1</xref>B). The two variants are found in both mixed stage and
embryonic-derived cDNA libraries and will not be further addressed. With the
exception of this predicted splice variant, the three cDNAs confirm the
intron/exon boundaries predicted by Genefinder for C39E9.14 (GI:3874851). Each
of the three cDNAs contains 20&#x2013;70 bases of 5&#x2032; sequence before the
predicted start codon, and none of the cDNAs contain an SL1 <italic>trans</italic>
splice leader sequence, suggesting <italic>dli-1</italic> is not processed by
<italic>trans</italic> splice machinery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Blumenthal,
1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>dli-1 Mutants Exhibit Failed Cell Divisions
in a Number of Postembryonic Lineages</title><p>Numerous postembryonic cell
lineages in <italic>dli-1</italic> mutants exhibit stochastic failed cell division
attempts. Lineages affected include the vulva precursor cells (VPCs) and their
descendents, male tail-specific cells, hypodermal cells, and cells of the gonad,
both germline and somatic. All of the affected lineages in wild-type animals
begin or continue divisions through the third and fourth (final) larval stage.
Early larval lineages are not affected in <italic>dli-1</italic> mutants, suggesting
successful cell divisions in the homozygous null mutants occurs until maternal
protein is depleted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Fay and Han,
2000</xref>).</p><p>The vulva in <italic>C. elegans</italic> is derived from three of
six equipotent cells, the VPCs, each of which undergoes three rounds of
divisions (beginning early in the third larval stage) to generate a total of 22
vulval-specific cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sulston and Horvitz,
1977</xref>). To address the nature of the aberrant vulva morphology observed in
the three alleles, we performed lineage analysis for the first two rounds of VPC
divisions in 15 <italic>ku266</italic> animals. Numerous stochastic failed cell division
attempts were observed. One, two, or all three VPCs failed the first division in
some animals, whereas in other animals, cells completed the first round of
division, and failed division attempts were only observed during the second
round. In each case, cells were observed to undergo nuclear envelope breakdown
(NEB), chromatin then appeared to condense, but &#x223C;20 min later, when two
daughter nuclei should appear, only a single nucleus reformed. These nuclei were
large and misshapen and often appeared to contain multiple nucleoli, suggesting
single polyploid nuclei (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B,
arrowheads). Also, several cells were seen to not attempt division at all.
Similar observations were made for male tail-specific cell division attempts.
These failed divisions were not cell lethal. Some cells that had failed division
attempts were seen to attempt division in the next round. Additionally, cells
that resulted from failed divisions were capable of expressing lineage-specific
markers.</p><fig id="F3"><caption><p>dli-1 alleles
undergo stochastic failed cell divisions in many postembryonic lineages. (A and
C) Wild-type <italic>C. elegans</italic> at late L4, the last larval stage before the
adult molt. (B and D) Similarly staged <italic>ku266</italic> animals. (A) Wild-type
late L4 vulva. Only 12 of 22 cells are visible in this plane of focus. (B)
<italic>ku266</italic> late L4 vulva. The enlarged nuclei are the result of failed
divisions. Several of these cells contain multiple nucleoli (arrowheads)
indicative of failed chromosome segregation<italic>.</italic> (C) Gonad of a wild-type
animal composed of many syncitial germline nuclei. (D) Germline nuclei in
<italic>ku266</italic> animals also have abnormal morphology and are probably polyploid
as a result of failed mitotic division in the distal end of the gonad arm. (E)
Wild-type somatic sheath cell nucleus visualized by staining with anti-CEH-18
antibodies. (F) Sheath cell nucleus of a <italic>ku266</italic> animal. Like all other
late postembryonic lineages observed, the somatic sheath cells also appear to
undergo failed division attempts, resulting in too few cells (average of 6 per
gonad arm compared with 10 in wild-type) with abnormal nuclear morphology. Bar,
&#x223C;10 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mk1011614003"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>The sterility of <italic>dli-1</italic> mutants is
also likely a result of failed mitotic divisions. The gonad in <italic>C.
elegans</italic> hermaphrodites consists of two U-shaped arms that terminate
proximally in a structure called the spermatheca and are joined by the uterus,
which opens, via the vulva, to the outside of the animal (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B38">Schedl, 1997</xref>). L1 animals possess a four-cell gonad primordium
consisting of two somatic and two germline precursor cells (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Sulston <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>). In
hermaphrodites, by L2, 10 somatic blast cells form a central somatic gonad
primordium. During L3 and L4, these blast cells divide to produce the sheath,
spermatheca, and uterus. Additionally, during late L3 and through adulthood, a
distal pool of nuclei within the syncitial gonad divide mitotically. The
resulting nuclei then enter meiosis, cellularize, and undergo gametogenesis.
During L4 these cells differentiate as spermatocytes, and after the L4-to-adult
molt, these cells begin differentiation as oocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B38">Schedl, 1997</xref>). The sheath of each gonad arm is composed of five
pairs of sheath cells, which are involved in regulating meiotic progression,
ooctye maturation, and ovulation of mature oocytes. Laser ablation of sheath
cells results in endomitotic germ cells and reduction of distal mitosis (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">McCarter <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Failed
division attempts are obvious in the distal end of gonads in <italic>dli-1</italic>
mutants, resulting in enlarged germline nuclei (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F3">3</xref>D). Additionally, <italic>ku266</italic> gonads stained with antibodies
against the POU domain containing homeobox protein CEH-18 (a gift from D.
Greenstein, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN), which is expressed only in
the somatic gonad cells, shows the nuclei of the sheath cells are large and have
irregular morphology compared with wild-type gonads similarly stained (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, E and F). Additionally, <italic>ku266</italic>
gonad arms contain on average six sheath cells (n = 15) compared with 10 in the
wild type. Loss of sheath cells could also contribute to irregular morphology
and the large size (as a result of endomitosis) of germ cells in <italic>dli-1</italic>
mutants.</p></sec><sec><title>Point Mutations in a Putative P-Loop Domain Can
Rescue dli-1 Phenotype</title><p>Previously reported sequence analysis of chick
and rat LIC suggests a conserved P-loop domain near the N terminus of the
protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gill <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>;
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). The
highest degree of similarity was found with the ABC transporter family of
ATPases. <italic>C. elegans</italic> DLI-1 sequence also shares similarity in this
region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, underlined). On the basis
of this observed similarity with ABC transporters, it was suggested LIC may be
an ATPase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gill <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>;
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>); however,
no experimental evidence has been published in support of this
suggestion.</p><p>Numerous lines of evidence suggest that a conserved lysine
residue within the P-loop of ATPases and other proteins such as kinases, which
also contain P-loops, is essential for the role of this domain (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Azzaria <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>; <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Deyrup <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Wu and Horvitz, 1998</xref>). An example is the <italic>C.
elegans</italic> proapoptotic ABC transporter-like gene <italic>ced-7</italic>. Arginine
substitutions for the conserved lysine residue in one of two P-loop domains in
CED-7 fail to rescue a <italic>ced-7</italic> cell corpse engulfment defect (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Wu and Horvitz, 1998</xref>). To test the necessity of
this putative P-loop domain in DLI-1, point mutations were constructed in the
minimal rescuing subclone pJHY10, generating both the conserved K59R (pJHY11)
and nonconserved K59A (pJHY14) substitutions. Both constructs completely rescued
the vulva cell division and sterility phenotypes in the two alleles tested,
<italic>ku266</italic> and <italic>ku287</italic>. In each case, rescued animals homozygous for
the two alleles were cultured for several generations and the efficiency of this
rescue was not observed to diminish. These data, therefore, suggest this region
is not essential for DLI-1 function.</p></sec><sec><title>DLI-1 Is Required for
Pronuclear Migration</title><p>Double-stranded RNA generated against a gene of
interest has been shown to specifically and potently disrupt that gene's
function in <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Fire <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Assuming that maternal protein from the heterozygous
parent of <italic>dli-1</italic> mutants allows homozygous progeny to develop normally
until that message is depleted, we performed RNAi against <italic>dli-1</italic> in both
wild-type and <italic>dli-1</italic> heterozygous animals to observe the earliest
phenotype.</p><p>In uninjected wild-type embryos, shortly after fertilization
the two meiotic divisions are completed, usually resulting in the extrusion of
two polar bodies at the anterior end of the embryo (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B1">Albertson, 1997</xref>). The resulting female pronucleus is positioned
slightly off the anterior cortex, whereas the male pronucleus, which contributes
the single centrosome, is tightly associated with the posterior cortex (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A). A pseudocleavage furrow partially
bisects the one-cell embryo. After duplication, the two daughter centrosomes
associated with the male pronuclear envelope separate and move to opposite sides
of the pronucleus while remaining associated with envelope (reviewed in <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Strome, 1993</xref>). The female and male pronuclei
then begin migration toward one another. The female pronucleus moves slightly
faster than the male and accelerates once it reaches the neck of the
pseudocleavege furrow. Consequently, the two pronuclei meet in the posterior end
of the embryo. After regression of the pseudocleavage furrow, the fused nuclei
along with the two associated centrosomes move anteriorly to the center of the
embryo. As the pronuclei undergo nuclear envelope breakdown, the centrosomes
rotate to align themselves along the anterior-posterior axis of the embryo and
the bipolar spindle is formed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, B
and C). Chromosome segregation follows, the embryo divides into two daughter
cells, and nuclear envelopes are reformed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F4">4</xref>D).</p><fig id="F4"><caption><p>Comparison of pronuclear migration in wild-type and
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. All images are oriented with anterior to the left.
(A&#x2013;D) Wild-type embryo; female (anterior) and male (posterior) pronuclei
begin migration before regression of the pseudocleavage furrow. The two
pronuclei meet and fuse before nuclear envelope breakdown. (E&#x2013;H) In the
majority (16/19) of <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos harvested from injected
wild-type mothers (shown) and 100&#x0025; of embryos harvested from injected
<italic>dli-1</italic> heterozygous mothers (n = 19), pronuclear migration does not
occur. (F) At the completion of pseudocleavage furrow regression, neither
pronucleus has initiated migration. (G) At a time point equivalent to that in B
in which the wild-type embryo is in metaphase, no pronuclear migration is
apparent, and the male pronucleus has undergone NEB before female pronuclear
NEB. (H) Multiple nuclei were formed in all <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos
observed (arrowheads). Timestamps are relative to completion of anterior
cytoplasmic contractions. In a wild-type embryo almost immediately after this,
the female pronucleus initiates posteriorward migration. Bar, &#x223C;10
&#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="mk1011614004" alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><p>RNAi against
<italic>C. elegans dhc-1</italic> results in early embryonic arrest, resulting from
failed cell divisions beginning in the one-cell stage <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryo
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).
Specifically, under Nomarski optics, male and female pronuclear migrations are
not observed, suggesting this motor protein is required for both migration
events. Also, a majority of <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos contained multiple
female pronuclei and aberrant polar body formation, suggesting defects in female
meiotic divisions.</p><p>RNAi against <italic>dli-1</italic> reveals it is also required
for pronuclear migration. Wild-type animals injected with double-stranded RNA
directed against <italic>dli-1</italic> are 100&#x0025; sterile 30 h after injection (n
&#x003E; 30). Embryos were first scored for number of female pronuclei and
pronuclear migration defects. Unlike <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi), 19/19
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos generated a single female pronucleus (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>E and Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>). In one of these embryos, polar body extrusion appeared
defective, resulting in one enlarged polar body. Although completion of meiosis
(as scored by the formation of a single female pronucleus) appeared mostly
unaffected, the majority of these embryos underwent failed pronuclear migration.
Male pronuclei migration was not observed in any of the 19 embryos. Complete
failure of female pronuclear migration was observed in 12/19 embryos (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, E&#x2013;H). For these 12 embryos, both
male and female pronuclei remained stationary through pseudocleavage furrow
regression. Shortly after completion of this event, the male pronucleus
underwent NEB, followed within 1&#x2013;2 min by female NEB. Such asynchronous
NEB events are common in mutants that exhibit failed pronuclear migration (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). The remaining
seven embryos showed varying degrees of female pronuclear migration. The female
pronucleus in four of these seven embryos migrated only to the midline of the
embryo, to the point of pseudocleavage furrow constriction, and then halted.
Thus, we scored these as failed migration events (Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>). In the remaining three embryos, the pronucleus did
successfully migrate to the posterior end; however, the rate of migration was
considerably decreased and the male and female pronuclei never fused before NEB.
</p><table-wrap id="T1"><caption><p>Summary of time-lapse
differential interference contrast and immunocytochemistry
analysis</p></caption>
<table><tr><th/>
<th>N2</th>
<th><italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi)</th>
<th><italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi)</th>
<th><italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) in
<italic>dli-1/</italic><sup>&#x002B;</sup></th></tr>
<tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr>
<tr><td>A. Multiple female pronuclei</td><td>0
/20</td><td>11 /14</td><td>0 /19</td><td>0 /19</td></tr><tr><td>B. Failed
pronuclear migration</td><td>0 /20</td><td>14 /14</td><td>16 /19</td><td>19
/19</td></tr><tr><td>C. Failed centrosome separation</td><td>0 /20</td><td>5
/5</td><td>10 /17</td><td>6 /8</td></tr><tr><td>D. Centrosomes dissociated from
male pronucleus</td><td>0 /20</td><td>n /d</td><td>5 /17</td><td>3
/8</td></tr><tr><td>E. Failure to form meiotic spindle</td><td>0 /15</td><td>7
/12</td><td>1 /11</td><td>1 /10</td></tr></table></table-wrap><p>We attempted to
increase the penetrance of the observed phenotypes by performing RNAi in a
<italic>dli-1</italic> heterozygous strain. As seen in the wild type, 100&#x0025; of
animals were sterile within 30 h after injection (n = 20). In 19/19 embryos a
single female pronucleus formed as in the wild-type, but 100&#x0025; of these
embryos failed to undergo either female or male pronuclear migration (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><p>In all 38 embryos, proper cell division did not occur.
Cleavage furrows were initiated in each embryo after NEB, but these furrows were
never able to completely bisect the embryos. Additionally, an ectopic cleavage
furrow was often initiated at the posterior cortex these embryos near the
nucleating microtubules. As in <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, multiple nuclei
reformed as the <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos progressed to interphase,
suggesting defects in chromosome segregation, or alternatively as a result of
failed metaphase chromosome congression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F4">4</xref>H, arrowheads).</p></sec><sec><title>Meiotic Spindle Formation
Is not Affected by dli-1(RNAi)</title><p>Dynein heavy chain and the IC subunit
have been shown to be necessary for meiotic spindle formation (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Palazzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Because
100&#x0025; of <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos formed a single female pronucleus,
we wanted to investigate meiosis in greater detail. Therefore, <italic>dli-1</italic>
and <italic>dhc-1(RNAi)</italic> embryos were stained with anti-&#x03B1;-tubulin and
DAPI to observe meiotic spindles and chromosomes. In wild-type embryos, after
fertilization, the two meiotic divisions proceed with the formation of an
acentrosomal meiotic spindle at each round surrounding the condensed metaphase
meiotic chromosomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, A&#x2013;C).
During each meiotic division, one set of oocyte chromosomes is extruded into a
polar body. When scored for meiotic spindle assembly, 19/21 observed
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos formed a meiotic spindle structure
indistinguishable from wild-type embryos (10/11 embryos from wild-type injection
and 9/10 embryos from <italic>dli-1</italic> heterozygous injections; Figure <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, D&#x2013;F, and Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>). In the <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo from a wild-type injected
mother in which a meiotic spindle was not observed, oocyte metaphase chromosomes
were scattered along the anterior cortex of the embryo and no polar body was
visible. In the other embryo (from an injected heterozygous mother), one polar
body had been extruded anteriorly, and the monovalent meiosis II chromosomes
were tightly condensed at the apex of the anterior cortex. In contrast, of 12
<italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos observed, only three had formed wild-type meiotic
spindles with metaphase chromosomes condensed at their centers. Two additional
embryos formed meiotic spindles, but the oocyte chromosomes were misplaced and
scattered outside of the structure. The remaining seven <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi)
embryos failed to form meiotic spindles, and their oocyte chromosomes were
randomly scattered throughout the anterior end of the embryos (Figure <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, G&#x2013;I, and Table <xref ref-type="table"
rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F5"><caption><p>Meiotic
spindles are formed in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, but not in all
<italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos observed. All embryos are oriented with anterior to
the left. (A, D, and G) Anti-tubulin staining to reveal microtubules. (B, E, and
H) DAPI staining to reveal DNA. (A&#x2013;C) Wild-type embryo at meiosis II. A
barrel-shaped spindle surrounds the female meiotic chromosomes. One polar body
has already been extruded (B and C, arrow). The male meiotic chromosomes are
tightly condensed at the posterior end of the embryo. (D&#x2013;F)
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo slightly later in meiosis II. A barrel-shaped
meiotic spindle has also formed around the condensed meiotic chromosomes. The
spindle has rotated to the anterior/posterior axis to complete the meiosis II
division. A single polar body has also already been extruded (E and F, arrow).
(G&#x2013;I) <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo. No meiotic spindle is observable and
the female meiotic chromosomes are scattered throughout the embryo. Bar,
&#x223C;10 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mk1011614005"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>DLI-1 Is Required for
Centrosome Separation and Attachment to Pronuclear Envelope</title><p>To more
accurately observe the effects that depletion of the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene product
has on centrosome separation and spindle orientation, we stained
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos with antibodies to ZYG-9, a conserved centrosome
protein (a gift from L. Matthews, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY) and
&#x03B1;-tubulin (a gift from M. Fuller, Stanford University, Stanford, CA).
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">G&#x00F6;nczy <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>
reported 100&#x0025; of <italic>dhc-</italic>1(RNAi) one-cell embryos exhibited failed
centrosome separation. We were able to faithfully duplicate these results (n =
5). Unlike <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, 7 of 17 <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos
from injected wild-type mothers, just before NEB or at metaphase had undergone
centrosome separation, but these centrosomes were never observed to undergo full
rotation, centration, or alignment along the anterior/posterior axis (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, D&#x2013;F). The remaining 10
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos were phenotypically indistinguishable from
<italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. Although centrosomes had duplicated, they had not
separated after NEB and progression into metaphase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
rid="F6">6</xref>, G&#x2013;I). Similar phenotypes were observed in embryos from
injected heterozygous mothers. Six of eight observed embryos had undergone
failed centrosome separation. In similar experiments, <xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B18">G&#x00F6;nczy <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref> observed 15&#x0025; of
centrosomes in <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos were disassociated from the male
pronuclei. This observation was also made in <italic>Drosophila</italic> heavy chain
mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Robinson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).
Similarly, centrosomes were dissociated from the male pronuclei in 5/17
(30&#x0025;) <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos from injected wild-type mothers and
3/8 embryos from heterozygous injections had dissociated centrosomes (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><fig id="F6"><caption><p>DLI-1 is required for centrosome separation in the one-cell
<italic>C. elegans</italic> embryo. Cytological analysis of metaphase embryos stained
for the centrosomal component ZYG-9, tubulin, or DNA as indicated. All images
are oriented with anterior to the left. (A&#x2013;C) Wild-type embryo at
metaphase. (A) Anti-ZYG-9 stains the two centrosomes that have rotated and
aligned along an anterior-posterior axis. (B) Centrosomes nucleate microtubules
forming the bipolar spindle visualized by anti-tubulin staining. (C) DAPI
staining shows chromosomes condensed to the metaphase plate. (D&#x2013;F)
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo in which centrosomes did separate. (D) Centrosomes
have separated but have failed to centrate. This panel represents the most
successful degree of rotation and spindle alignment observed. (E and F)
Centrosomes do nucleate microtubules and chromosomes are condensed but have not
yet congressed to a metaphase plate. (G&#x2013;I) <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo
exhibiting the most severe centrosome separation phenotype. (G) Some embryos
(10/17) from wild-type injections failed to separate centrosomes and therefore
formed no bipolar spindle. (H) Microtubules are nucleated and chromosomes have
condensed and congressed to a metaphase plate (I). Embryos from heterozygous
injections (7/8) were phenotypically identical to the embryo in G&#x2013;I. Bar,
&#x223C;10 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mk1011614006"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig><fig id="F7"><caption><p>Centrosomes are dissociated from the male pronucleus in
32&#x0025; of <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi). In 5/17 embryos from
wild-type&#x2013;injected mothers and 3/8 embryos from <italic>dli-1</italic>
heterozygous injected mothers, centrosomes (arrows) were dissociated from the
male pronucleus (arrowheads). (A&#x2013;D) Embryo from a <italic>dli-1</italic>
heterozygous-injected mother showing centrosomes as visualized by anti-ZYG-9
staining (A), microtubules visualized by anti-tubulin staining (B), DAPI
staining to reveal DNA (C), and merged (D). Bar, &#x223C;10
&#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xlink:href="mk1011614007"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>DHC-1 Is Correctly Localized
in dli-1 RNAi Embryos</title><p>The phenotypic similarity between
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) and <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos raises the question of
whether the <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) phenotype is directly related to the function
of the gene product or the result of ablating DHC-1 function through disruption
of the cytoplasmic dynein complex itself. To address this question,
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos were stained with antibodies to <italic>C. elegans</italic>
DHC-1 (a gift from P. G&#x00F6;nczy and A. Hyman, EMBL, Heidelberg, Germany). In
wild-type embryos, DHC-1 is distributed throughout the cytoplasm in a punctate
manner, localizes to the cell cortex, and is enriched at the periphery of both
the male and female pronuclei before NEB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). During prometaphase, DHC-1 is enriched on both
sides of congressing chromosomes, and at metaphase and anaphase it is
additionally enriched on the spindle on both sides of the metaphase plate
(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>A) and between segregating
chromosomes, respectively. Compared with wild-type and <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi)
embryos, DHC-1 appears to localize correctly in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. We
were unable to faithfully reproduce the pronuclear envelope staining pattern in
wild-type embryos; however, metaphase and anaphase DHC-1 staining clearly shows
DHC-1 localized to metaphase chromosomes and spindles. Therefore, we focused on
metaphase and prometaphase staining in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos to score for
correct DHC-1 localization. In several <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, due to
failed centrosome separation, nothing similar to a bipolar spindle is formed and
therefore spindle staining could not be observed. However, in these embryos
DHC-1 still clearly localizes to prometaphase and metaphase chromosomes (Figure
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>G). Additionally, when centrosome
separation does occur, DHC-1 can be seen to localize in a pattern similar to the
metaphase spindle staining seen in wild-type embryos (compare Figure <xref
ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, A and E). These data suggest the phenotypes
observed in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos are specific to loss of DLI-1 and not
strictly a result of disrupting the cytoplasmic dynein complex.</p><fig
id="F8"><caption><p>DHC-1 localizes correctly in
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. (A) DHC-1 localization to the mitotic spindle in a
wild-type metaphase embryo. (B) The same wild-type embryo stained with DAPI to
reveal metaphase chromosomes. (C and D) <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo also at
metaphase. DHC-1 localizes to either side of the condensed metaphase chromosomes
and the mitotic spindle. Centrosomes have apparently separated enough in this
embryo for a mitotic spindle to form. (E and F) <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo also
at metaphase. No DHC-1 staining is detectable. (G and H) Posterior end of a
<italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryo as chromosomes are condensing at metaphase. When
centrosomes fail to separate and no spindle is formed, DHC-1 staining is still
observed on metaphase (arrowhead) and prometaphase (arrow) chromosomes. Bars,
&#x223C;10 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mk1011614008"
alt-version="yes"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec
sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We describe phenotypic characterization
of the first mutant alleles of cytoplasmic dynein LIC, which we have named
<italic>dli-1</italic>. Unlike the dynein motor protein and other subunits of the dynein
complex, LIC is restricted to the cytoplasmic dynein complex and has no homolog
in axonemal dynein (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">King,
2000</xref>). This suggests LIC may be required for discrete aspects of dynein's
function. Support for a role in mitosis is found in the recent observation that
LIC directly interacts with pericentrin, a conserved centrosome component (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Purohit <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>The three
loss-of-function alleles we have isolated in <italic>C. elegans</italic> also suggest a
requirement for the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene product during mitosis. Homozygous
animals are sterile and many postembryonic cell lineages undergo stochastic
failed division attempts. Affected cell lineages are those that continue
division attempts through late larval stages in wild-type animals. Early larval
lineages appear unaffected in <italic>dli-1</italic> mutants. These observations suggest
enough maternal product or message is available during embryogenesis and early
larval development to allow proper cell division to occur.</p><p>The precise
role that LIC plays during cell division is still not understood. Previous
analysis of LIC peptide sequences led to the speculation that LIC may be an
ATPase and serve a regulatory role for dynein's function through this activity
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gill <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). This suggestion
is based on identification of a putative P-loop domain within the protein
sequence. The P-loop (or Walker A box) is one of three conserved motifs found in
numerous nucleotide-hydrolyzing proteins, including the ABC transporter family
of ATPases, and is defined by the consensus sequence GXXXXGK(S/T) (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Walker <italic>et al.</italic>, 1982</xref>). Although this
consensus is present in all LIC sequences found to date, the other two motifs
(the Walker B box and the signature motif) are not present. Additionally,
previous work has shown a conserved lysine residue (corresponding to K59 in
<italic>dli-1</italic>) within the P-loop sequence is required for proper nucleotide
binding and therefore ATPase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Wu and
Horvitz, 1998</xref>). Amino acid substitutions at K59 in our rescuing construct
to either alanine or the conservative arginine residue are still able to confer
complete rescue in the <italic>dli-1</italic> alleles for multiple generations of
homozygous animals. This suggests that nucleotide binding is not required for
DLI-1 function and that DLI-1 is not an ATPase.</p><p>To circumvent maternal
rescue and observe the earliest phenotype for depletion of DLI-1, we have used
RNAi to specifically inhibit function of the <italic>dli-1</italic> gene product. As
expected, a much earlier requirement for <italic>dli-1</italic>, than observed in our
mutants was revealed. The resulting phenotypes suggest DLI-1 is required for
many of dynein's mitotic functions, but potentially not for dynein's role in
meiotic spindle formation. When RNAi is performed against the <italic>C.
elegans</italic> dynein heavy chain <italic>dhc-1</italic>, numerous female pronuclei are
formed in one-cell embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gonczy <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Additionally, when RNAi is performed against two
subunits of the dynactin complex, p150<sup>glued</sup> or p50/dynamintin,
multiple female pronuclei are also observed, although at a much smaller
percentage compared with <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B18">Gonczy <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). In all <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi)
embryos observed, whether the injected mother was wild type or heterozygous,
only a single female pronucleus is formed. Additionally, anti-tubulin antibody
staining in early <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos shows meiotic spindles are formed
and meiotic chromosomes are condensed and correctly localized within the spindle
(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, D&#x2013;F). However, meiotic
spindles are only seen in 5/12 <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. Additionally, two
of these five embryos show chromosomes scattered outside of the meiotic spindle.
These data cannot be used as conclusive evidence that DLI-1 is not required for
meiotic spindle formation whereas DHC-1 is, because these are static
observations, and the <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos could have been fixed before
or in between meiotic spindle formation. An alternative explanation is that even
in injected heterozygotes, <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) is incompletely penetrant and
only a small amount of protein is required for proper dynein function during
meiosis. Defects in meiotic spindle formation, however, would account for
missegregation of meiotic chromosomes and the formation of multiple female
pronuclei in <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. Because LIC has been shown to
interact with the centrosome component pericentrin, and meiotic spindles form
without centrosomes, it is still an attractive possibility that meiotic spindle
formation is not affected in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos because DLI-1 is not
required for meiotic spindle formation.</p><p>The pronuclear migration defects
observed in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos suggests LIC is required for this
aspect of dynein motor function. The majority of <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos
from wild-type injections underwent failed pronuclear migration (16/19), and
100&#x0025; of embryos from heterozygous injections showed failed pronuclear
migration Interestingly, alleles of most other subunits of the cytoplasmic
dynein complex as well as components of the dynactin complex have been isolated
in genetic screens for defective nuclear migration in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and
<italic>N. crassa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Plamann <italic>et al.</italic>,
1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Xiang <italic>et al.</italic>,
1994</xref>). Although LIC mutants were not isolated in these screens, our RNAi
data show <italic>dli-1</italic> is required at least for pronuclear migration and
potentially, therefore, in other nuclear migration events.</p><p>DLI-1 also
appears to be required for centrosome separation. Although centrosome separation
occurred in 9/25 <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, the spindle that was formed
failed to centrate and the centrosomes never completely migrated to opposite
poles of the male pronucleus. Again, incomplete penetrance could explain the
9/25 embryos in which centrosomes did separate from one another. Additionally,
in 32&#x0025; (8/25) of <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos, centrosomes were
dissociated from the male pronulcear envelope. This phenotype was also observed
in 15&#x0025; of <italic>dhc-1</italic>(RNAi) embryos. These data are not surprising
because LIC has been shown to directly interact with the conserved centrosome
component pericentrin. Loss of this interaction through <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi) may
increase disassociation of centrosomes from the nuclear envelope.</p><p>Dynein
LIC is required for the function of the dynein motor complex. However, like
other subunits of this complex, a specific role has yet to be defined. Numerous
light chain subunits are found associated with the dynein motor complex and have
been shown to be required not only for certain dynein functions such as nuclear
migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Beckwith <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>)
but also for interacting with proteins that are not currently implicated in
dynein's mitotic roles such as Bcl-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
rid="B35">Puthalakath <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) and neuronal nitric-oxide
synthase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Jaffrey and Snyder,
1996</xref>).</p><p>The observed interaction between LIC and pericentrin (<xref
ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Purohit <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) suggests a
mechanism for at least two of the requirements we have shown for DLI-1:
centrosome separation and centrosome association with the male pronucleus. The
dynein motor complex could be localized to the microtubule-organizing centers
through such an interaction, allowing it to provide the force necessary to
separate centrosomes and align the bipolar spindle. This interaction, however,
does not explain the pronuclear migration defect seen in <italic>dli-1</italic>(RNAi)
embryos. Pronuclear migration defects are also seen after RNAi of dynein light
chain (<italic>dlc-1)</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Gonczy <italic>et al.</italic>,
2000</xref>). Both observations, therefore, may result from mislocalization of
the dynein motor complex.</p><p>It seems unlikely that LIC is playing only a
structural role for the dynein motor complex. The protein has been shown to
exist as numerous phosphorylated species, and this phosphorylation is regulated
in a cell cycle-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gill <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>,
1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Niclas <italic>et al.</italic>,
1996</xref>). Mapping LIC's interaction domains and analyzing the regulation of
its phosphorylation should begin to shed more light on the nature of its role
within the dynein
complex.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank David
Fay and Li Yan for isolating two of the <italic>dli-1</italic> alleles. We thank Pierre
G&#x00F6;nczy and Tony Hyman (EMBL, Heidelberg, Germany) for anti-DHC-1
antibodies, Lisa Matthews (Cornell University, Ithaca, NY) for anti-ZYG-9
antibodies, and David Greenstein (Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN) for
anti-CEH-18 antibodies. We also thank Yuji Kohara for providing cDNAs and Alan
Coulson for cosmids. Some strains used in this work were obtained from the
Caenorhabditis Genetics Center. We thank Dan Starr and David Fay for helpful
discussions and comments on the manuscript. J.Y. was supported by a National
Institutes of Health Predoctoral Training Grant. This work was supported by a
grant from the Public Health Service (GM-47869) and Howard Hughes Medical
Institute of which M.H. is an assistant
investigator.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="B1"><citation><name><surname>Albertson</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal
</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><article-title><italic>
C. elegans</italic> II</article-title><source>C. elegans
II</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Cold
Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name><fpage>47</fpage><lpage
>78</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref
id="B2"><citation><name><surname>Azzaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Schurr</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Discrete mutations introduced in the predicted nucleotide-binding sites
of the mdr1 gene abolish its ability to confer multidrug
resistance</article-title><source>Mol. Cell.
Biol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5289</fpage><lpage>5297
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B3"><citation><name><surname>Barstead</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Kleiman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Cloning, sequencing, and mapping of an alpha-actinin gene from the
nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Cell Motil.
Cytoskeleton</source><year>1991</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage
>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B4"><citation><name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Roghi</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ronald Morris</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><article-title>The
&#x201C;8-kD&#x201D; cytoplasmic dynein light chain is required for nuclear
migration and for dynein heavy chain localization in <italic>Aspergillus
nidulans</italic></article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>
1247</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B5"><citation><name><surname>Bielli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Thornqvist</surname><given-names>P.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrick</surname><given-names>A.G.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald
</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaffrey</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The small GTPase Rab4A interacts with the central region of cytoplasmic
dynein light intermediate chain-1</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res.
Commun.</source><year>2001</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>
1153</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B6"><citation><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>T.a.S.,
K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal
</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><article-title>RNA Processing and Gene
Structure</article-title><source>C. elegans II</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory
Press</publisher-name><fpage>117</fpage>
<lpage>145</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B7"><citation><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Patel-King</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benashski</surname><given-names>S.E.
</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaffery</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Goldstein</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> roadblock and <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> LC7: a
conserved family of dynein-associated proteins involved in axonal transport,
flagellar motility, and mitosis</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>180
</lpage></citation></ref>

<ref
id="B8"><citation><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><article-title>The
genetics of <italic>Caenorhabditis
elegans</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1974
</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref
id="B9"><citation><name><surname>Deyrup</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Krishnan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockburn</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name><article-title>Deletion and
site-directed mutagenesis of the ATP-binding motif (P-loop) in the bifunctional
murine ATP-sulfurylase/adenosine 5&#x2032;-phosphosulfate kinase
enzyme</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>9450</fpage><lpage>
9456</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref
id="B10"><citation><name><surname>Dillman
III</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabney</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein is
associated with slow axonal transport</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>144
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B11"><citation><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Shakes</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><source>Caenorhabditis elegans:
modern biological analysis of an
organism</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>San
Diego, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref
id="B12"><citation><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han
</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Mutations in cye-1, a <italic>Caenorhabditis
elegans</italic> cyclin E homolog, reveal coordination between cell-cycle control
and vulval development &#x005B;In Process
Citation&#x005D;</article-title><source>Development</source><year>
2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>4049</fpage><lpage>4060</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B13"><citation><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname
><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Kostas</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Driver</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names
></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><article-title>Potent and
specific genetic interference by double-stranded RNA in <italic>Caenorhabditis
elegans</italic> &#x005B;see
comments&#x005D;</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998
</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>811</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B14"><citation><name><surname>Gaglio</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Dionne</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Mitotic spindle poles are organized by structural and motor
proteins in addition to centrosomes</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>
1066</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B15"><citation><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Cleveland</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroer</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Characterization of DLC-A and DLC-B, two families of cytoplasmic
dynein light chain subunits</article-title><source>Mol. Biol.
Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>654
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B16"><citation><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Schroer</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szilak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Steuer</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheetz</surname><given-names
>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><article-title>
Dynactin, a conserved, ubiquitously expressed component of an activator of
vesicle motility mediated by cytoplasmic dynein</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>
1650</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B17"><citation><name><surname>Gonczy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Echeverri</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oegema</surname><given-names>K.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S
.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Duperon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oegema</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassin</surname><given-names>E.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkham</surname
><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Flohrs</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goessen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leidel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alleaume</surname><given-names>A.M.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozlu</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Hyman</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><article-title>Functional genomic analysis of cell
division in <italic>C. elegans</italic> using RNAi of genes on chromosome III &#x005B;In
Process
Citation&#x005D;</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000
</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>336</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B18"><citation><name><surname>Gonczy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Pichler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkham</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein is
required for distinct aspects of MTOC positioning, including centrosome
separation, in the one cell stage <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
embryo</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>150
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B19"><citation><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Hird</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name
><name><surname>Andachi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohara</surname><given-names>Y.
</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finney</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><article-title>
Targeted mutations in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> POU homeo box gene
ceh-18 cause defects in oocyte cell cycle arrest, gonad migration, and epidermal
differentiation</article-title><source>Genes
Dev.</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1948
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B20"><citation><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Vaughan</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskovits</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names
></name><name><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular
analysis of a cytoplasmic dynein light intermediate chain reveals homology to a
family of ATPases</article-title><source>J. Cell
Sci.</source><year>1995</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B21"><citation><name><surname>Jaffrey</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Snyder</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><article-title>PIN: an associated protein inhibitor
of neuronal nitric oxide
synthase</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>274</volume>
<fpage>774</fpage><lpage>777</lpage>
</citation></ref><ref
id="B22"><citation><name><surname>Karki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Holzbaur</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><article-title>Affinity chromatography
demonstrates a direct binding between cytoplasmic dynein and the dynactin
complex</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>28806</fpage><lpage>
28811</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B23"><citation><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><article-title>The
dynein microtubule motor</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys.
Acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>1496</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>75
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B24"><citation><name><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Haimo</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein is a vesicle
protein</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source><year>1992</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>4793</fpage><lpage>
4798</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B25"><citation><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Carter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierry-Mieg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Kemphues</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>ZYG-9, a
<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> protein required for microtubule organization
and function, is a component of meiotic and mitotic spindle
poles</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>
1168</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B26"><citation><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Bartlett</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><article-title>Soma-germ cell interactions
in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>: multiple events of hermaphrodite germline
development require the somatic sheath and spermathecal
lineages</article-title><source>Dev.
Biol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>143
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B27"><citation><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Kramer</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinchcomb</surname><given-names>D.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><article-title>Efficient gene
transfer in <italic>C. elegans</italic>: extrachromosomal maintenance and integration of
transforming sequences</article-title><source>EMBO
J.</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3959</fpage><lpage>3970
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B28"><citation><name><surname>Niclas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan
</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cell cycle regulation of dynein association with membranes modulates
microtubule-based organelle transport</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>593
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B29"><citation><name><surname>Nurminsky</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Nurminskaya</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benevolenskaya</surname><given-names>E.
V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevelyov</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Hartl</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gvozdev</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein intermediate-chain isoforms with different
targeting properties created by tissue-specific alternative
splicing</article-title><source>Mol. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6816</fpage><lpage>6825
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B30"><citation><name><surname>Palazzo</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Vaisberg</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names></name><article-title>Dynein is required for spindle assembly in
cytoplasmic extracts of <italic>Spisula solidissima</italic> oocytes</article-title><source>J.
Cell
Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>302
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B31"><citation><name><surname>Plamann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Minke</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinsley</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein
and actin-related protein Arp1 are required for normal nuclear distribution in
filamentous fungi</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>149
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B32"><citation><name><surname>Presley</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Cole</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroer</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaal</surname><given-names
>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>ER-to-Golgi transport visualized in living cells &#x005B;see
comments&#x005D;</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997
</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>85</lpage> </citation></ref><ref
id="B33"><citation><name><surname>Pulak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Anderson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><article-title>mRNA surveillance by the
<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> smg genes</article-title><source>Genes
Dev.</source><year>1993</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1897
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B34"><citation><name><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Tynan</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doxsey</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><article-title>Direct interaction of
pericentrin with cytoplasmic dynein light intermediate chain contributes to
mitotic spindle organization</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>492
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B35"><citation><name><surname>Puthalakath</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Huang</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names
>A.</given-names></name><article-title>The proapoptotic activity of the Bcl-2 family member
Bim is regulated by interaction with the dynein motor
complex</article-title><source>Mol.
Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>296
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B36"><citation><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Blumenthal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><source>C. elegans II</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory
Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref
id="B37"><citation><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Wojcik</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>McGrail</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>T.
S.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein is required for the nuclear
attachment and migration of centrosomes during mitosis in
<italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>608
</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref
id="B38"><citation><name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal
</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name>
<surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><article-title>
Developmental genetics of the germ line</article-title><source>C. elegans II</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory
Press</publisher-name><fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>269</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B39"><citation><name><surname>Skop</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>White
</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><article-title>The dynactin complex is required for
cleavage plane specification in early <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
embryos</article-title><source>Curr.
Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1110</fpage><lpage>1116
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B40"><citation><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Roush</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nester</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> VirB11 protein requires a consensus
nucleotide-binding site for function in virulence</article-title><source>J.
Bacteriol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>
36</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B41"><citation><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><article-title>
Determination of cleavage
planes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>
3</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B42"><citation><name><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Horvitz</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><article-title>Post-embryonic cell lineages of the
nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Dev.
Biol.</source><year>1977</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>156
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B43"><citation><name><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Schierenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><article-title>The embryonic cell
lineage of the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Dev.
Biol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>119
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B44"><citation><name><surname>Tynan</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Purohit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doxsey</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><article-title>Light intermediate
chain 1 defines a functional subfraction of cytoplasmic dynein which binds to
pericentrin &#x005B;In Process Citation&#x005D;</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>32763</fpage><lpage>
32768</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B45"><citation><name><surname>Vaisberg</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Koonce</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein plays a role in mammalian mitotic spindle
formation</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>858
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B46"><citation><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Vallee</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein binds dynactin
through a direct interaction between the intermediate chains and
p150Glued</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1507</fpage><lpage>
1516</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B47"><citation><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Saraste</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Runswick</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><article-title>Distantly related
sequences in the alpha- and beta-subunits of ATP synthase, myosin, kinases and
other ATP-requiring enzymes and a common nucleotide binding
fold</article-title><source>EMBO
J.</source><year>1982</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>951
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B48"><citation><name><surname>Wordeman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Mitchison</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><article-title>Identification and partial
characterization of mitotic centromere-associated kinesin, a kinesin-related
protein that associates with centromeres during mitosis &#x005B;see
comments&#x005D;</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>104
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B49"><citation><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvitz
</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><article-title>The <italic>C. elegans</italic> cell corpse
engulfment gene ced-7 encodes a protein similar to ABC
transporters</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>93</volume>
<fpage>951</fpage><lpage>960</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B50"><citation><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Beckwith</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names>
</name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein is involved in nuclear migration in
<italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>2100</fpage><lpage>2104
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B51"><citation><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roghi
</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Characterization and localization of the cytoplasmic dynein heavy chain
in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>9890</fpage><lpage>9894
</lpage></citation></ref><ref
id="B52"><citation><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>
Dictenberg</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names>
</name><name><surname>Tuft</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doxsey</surname><given-names>S.
J.</given-names></name><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein-mediated assembly of pericentrin and
gamma tubulin onto centrosomes</article-title><source>Mol. Biol.
Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2047</fpage><lpage>2056
</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article><?mtl /hellip?> 
