<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../../Ncbi/ArchivingDTD/DTD/Working/archivearticle.dtd">
<article>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">BR MED J</journal-id>
<issn>0959-8138</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>British Medical Journal</publisher-name>
</publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>bmj-4619-a6</article-id> 
<article-categories>
<subj-group>
<subject>General Practice</subject>
<subject>11</subject>
<subject>9</subject>
<subject>76</subject>
<subject>215</subject>
<subject>110</subject>
<subject>318</subject>
</subj-group>
<series-title>Controversy in primary care</series-title>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Should asymptomatic haemochromatosis 
be treated?</article-title></title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="pub"><day>13</day>
<month>5</month><year>2000</year></pub-date>
<volume>320</volume><issue>7245</issue>
<fpage>1314</fpage>
<lpage>1317</lpage>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, 
British Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body><p>Genetic testing <?mtl hellip?>now allows haemochromatosis to be
diagnosed before symptoms emerge. Testing is potentially beneficial
because early treatment of iron overload is the only way to prevent
organ damage. Treatment by venesection is, however, lengthy and can
have a detrimental effect on quality of life, and not all patients with
the mutation will develop symptoms. A general practitioner and her
patient describe their experience of treatment of asymptomatic
haemochromatosis and ask whether it was really necessary. Their
experiences are commented on by a general practitioner and a consultant
haematologist.<?mtl /hellip?></p>
</body>

<sub-article>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">BR MED J</journal-id>
<issn>0959-8138</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>British Medical Journal</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Treatment can be onerous for patient and
doctor</article-title></title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name>
<surname>Seamark</surname>
<given-names>Clare J</given-names></name>
<role>general practitioner</role>
<xref ref-type="aff"><sup><italic>a</italic></sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchinson</surname>
<given-names>Margaret</given-names></name>
<role>retired headmistress</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Honiton
Group Practice, Honiton, Devon EX14 2NY</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn><p>Correspondence to: C Seamark 
<email>daseamark@msn.com</email></p></fn>
<fn><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>07</day><month>2</month>
<year>2000</year></date>
</history>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, 
British Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
</article-meta>
</front>

<body>
<p>The development of genetic testing for disease has
raised the problem of whether to test asymptomatic
individuals. <?mtl hellip?><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-1"></xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-2"></xref> Hereditary haemochromatosis is one such
disease for which testing is possible. The associated gene, HFE
(previously HLA-H), was identified in 1996 together with
two mutations C282Y and H63D.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-3"></xref> The C282Y mutation is
present in about 90&percnt; of known cases in the United
Kingdom.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-4"></xref> The condition may be more prevalent (possibly
one in 300) than previously thought. Patients do not usually
develop symptoms until they are over 40 years old, by which time
deposition of iron in organs such as the liver, pancreas, heart,
and endocrine systems may have caused irreversible tissue
damage.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-5"></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-6"></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-7"></xref> Repeated venesection is an effective
treatment and can restore normal life expectancy in people with no
evidence of organ damage. In women the onset may be later as
menstruation provides physiological blood loss.<?mtl /hellip?></p>
<?mtl hellip?><p>In 1997, MH was 67 and had had type 2 diabetes for five years. The
disease was well controlled with an oral sulphonylurea. She took part
in a study (which had ethical approval) to look at the genetic
aetiology of diabetes and the role of haemochromatosis. She was found
to be homozygous for the C282Y mutation. She was informed of this as
she might have or develop complications from the condition. Subsequent
tests confirmed the mutation status and showed a ferritin concentration
of &gt;1000 &mgr;g/l (normal range 12-110 &mgr;g/l). A review in the
gastroenterology clinic showed no evidence of hepatic dysfunction and
no symptoms attributable to haemochromatosis. She was advised to have
venesection to prevent problems in the future. She and her general
practitioner write about their experiences.</p>
<sec><title>General practitioner&apos;s view</title>
<p>Before MH&apos;s case I knew little about haemochromatosis, having
seen only a handful of cases of &ldquo;bronzed diabetes&rdquo; during my
hospital training. I discussed the finding with my colleagues and,
after liaison with the hospital team, contacted MH to explain that a
potentially important finding had come from the study. MH came to the
appointment with her family tree. Muscular dystrophy was already known
in her family, and the tree was marked with carriers and affected
individuals. I explained that a different condition had been found. It
was arranged that MH should see a gastroenterologist and contact
her immediate family regarding the need for testing. MH had no
children. She had one brother and two sisters. One sister had a son and
daughter. Only her unmarried sister is still being investigated. MH&apos;s
brother and father also had diabetes so it is probable that MH&apos;s
diabetes was unrelated to the haemochromatosis.</p>
<p>I initially had the impression that active treatment might not be
needed, just monitoring of liver function. Regular venesection was,
however, recommended to prevent complications of the disease. As she
lived 16 miles from the district general hospital I was asked if she
could have venesection at our local community hospital. I agreed to
this as it made good use of the community hospital and saved MH
travelling, although at the time I did not realise all it would entail
or the time it would take.</p>
<p>It soon became clear that we were not making much impact on MH&apos;s serum
ferritin concentrations and that it would take many venesections to
reach the normal range (figure). On further reading I discovered it
could take a year, something I did not immediately share with MH. At
times we both became dispirited, especially when because of holidays
the concentration started to rise again. Fortunately we got on well so
we were able to pass the time during the venesection in a reasonably
pleasurable way. However, it was a lot more demanding than I had
imagined. Venous access was not easy so I had to do most
sessions. <fig><caption><p>Serum ferritin concentration and venesection patterns (values
over 1000 &mgr;g/l have been designated as 1100)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="seac5289.f1"/></fig></p>
<p>MH had to cancel her trip to Ascension Island, where she had worked for
many years, because with even the slightest break from venesection her
ferritin concentration rose and she did not want to risk being away for
a few weeks at that time. The other problem was we forgot her diabetes.
When she felt tired she put it down to the venesection, and it took a
while to realise that it was in fact due to a deterioration in her
diabetes. I was determined she should not miss her trip to New Zealand
in early 1999. She was able to arrange venesection there and went armed
with her computerised records and results.</p>
<p>It has taken a long time and many venesections (about 40) to get her
serum ferritin concentration down. At the beginning of 2000 it was
within normal range. We are now able to manage with venesection at 4-6
weekly intervals, and MH has resumed her travelling and her diabetic
control has also improved. She has just celebrated her 70th birthday in
New York.</p>
</sec>
<sec><title>Patient&apos;s view</title>
<sec><title>March 1998</title>
<p>Diabetes has definitely affected my family. My father had
to have insulin injections. It was a nerve racking experience which
didn&apos;t help my parents&apos; relationship, and in the end they parted.
When I was first diagnosed I was angry and frightened, though I soon
realised that matters might have been a lot worse. My brother has
become a bit bowed down by his diabetes, but he is more seriously
affected.</p>
<p>At present neither I nor my family have much idea what haemochromatosis
entails so we are just intrigued. I should have a clearer picture once
I have talked to the consultant. As a family we would be pleased to
answer any questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec><title>July 1998</title>
<p>I have now been having blood taken regularly at Honiton
Hospital by CS for two months. Afterwards I have around 48 hours of
lethargy and find it hard to do my usual activities. I am sleeping
longer, often 8-9 hours at night and for an hour or so in the
afternoons. In mid-July we had to revert to weekly bloodletting after
the blood test showed the iron count had gone up. I was too tired for
the rest of the week to do anything else and feel I may have to
reconsider my trip to Ascension Island in August. I went back to see
the consultant, but unfortunately only saw a junior doctor who didn&apos;t
give me much confidence.</p>
<p>At the beginning I could not perceive how haemochromatosis would affect
me unduly as I felt so well. It has meant, however, that I lose two
days a week because my normal energy levels are lowered. I have forgone
my trip to Ascension Island, where I lived and worked for 17 years, in
order not to jeopardise the treatment, and I will probably not be
invited to do the job I was going to do there. Now I am worried about
my trip to New Zealand and Australia in January 1999. If I cancel that
I will lose a lot of money, which is worrying. I try not to think about
it, but it is difficult.</p>
<p>I also feel that CS is getting a raw deal. I have really appreciated
her accompanying me and taking the blood&mdash;I am a baby when it comes to
hospitals, etc. However, I feel that she is acting over and beyond the
call of duty and I realise she may have to hand me over. I just hope it
will be to someone as skilled as she is.</p>
<p>I suppose that I am becoming weary of it all, now that it is affecting
my life. What if it takes another six months or so before I&apos;ve
contained this condition and the iron count is at an acceptable level,
and what happens after that?</p>
</sec>
<sec><title>Late 1998</title>
<p>The bloodletting continued, usually weekly, but
occasionally two weekly. Although I cancelled my working holiday on
Ascension Island because I didn&apos;t feel 100&percnt; after the bloodletting, I
decided that come what may I was going to New Zealand. But how was I to
do this and not return to square one as far as the ferritin count is
concerned? CS suggested that I wrote to my friends in New Zealand to
see if something could be arranged at their local hospital, and I
received word that it could.</p>
</sec>
<sec><title>June 1999</title>
<p>I went to New Zealand in January and had four treatments at
a hospital there. I had several blood tests, and they were kind and
thorough and gave me results to bring home. I have had five sessions
since my return, but the last have been poor with only about half a
unit taken before the flow stopped. Still, the ferritin level has
fallen to 180 or slightly below. The sad thing is that it does not look
as though I will ever get back to Ascension as the booking system has
changed and it will be too expensive.</p>
<p>It is over a year since I began this course, and I frankly feel sorry
the condition was ever discovered&mdash;little did I realise how it would
dominate my everyday life. I don&apos;t usually have any after effects
these days, but even so my diary revolves around my visits to the
hospital, and I grow weary of it. I am sure my doctors have similar
feelings at times. Were it not for CS and all her support, so I feel I
cannot let her down, I would have given up long ago. I was quite
shocked to realise that this would go on for life&mdash;albeit less
frequently, but still a drag. However, I have to count myself fortunate
that it is not a life threatening condition and that knowing about it
means that it can be monitored&mdash;alongside diabetes it is merely an
irritant. I try to look at it all objectively.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Population screening should ideally be promoted only when
the natural course of the condition is known. Recent studies suggest
that genetic screening for haemochromatosis will reveal many
asymptomatic people,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-8"></xref> for whom the benefits of treatment
are not yet clear.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-9"></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-10"></xref> Although the condition is more
common than previously realised, there may be differences in genetic
expression, with some people less likely to be clinically
affected.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-11"></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-12"></xref></p>
<p>We hope that this account of how the treatment for asymptomatic
haemochromatosis has affected MH has contributed to the discussion
about whether to screen for haemochromatosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-13"></xref> In many
ways MH feels she would rather not have known as she has seen no
obvious benefit to herself or her family, and it has had a detrimental
effect on the quality of her life and it constantly intrudes on her
life. At present it is not possible for her medical advisers to
quantify how treatment may have improved her long term health. We hope
that we will prevent the complications of haemochromatosis, but we will
never know now whether she would have developed them. For her general
practitioner it has meant a lot of extra work that, although willingly
undertaken, would not have been part of general medical services.</p>
</sec><?mtl /hellip?>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank MH&apos;s family for their willingness to be involved in
genetic testing <?mtl hellip?>and agreeing to the story being told; David Seamark,
who suggested the paper and provided constant encouragement; and the
staff of Honiton Hospital who helped with the venesection. The Honiton
Group Practice is an NHS Funded Research Practice.<?mtl /hellip?></p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<?mtl hellip?>
<ref id="B1-1"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-2"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-3"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-4"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-5"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-6"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-7"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-8"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-9"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-10"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-11"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-12"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B1-13"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<?mtl /hellip?>
</ref-list>
</back>
</sub-article>

<sub-article><?mtl hellip?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">BR MED J</journal-id>
<issn>0959-8138</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>British Medical Journal</publisher-name>
</publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group>
<subject>Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Commentary: False certainty of clinical 
guidance</article-title></title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name>
<surname>Heath</surname><given-names>Iona</given-names></name>
<role>general practitioner</role><xref ref-type="aff">
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>45 Canonbury 
Park South, London N1 2JL</aff>
<author-notes><fn><p>Correspondence to: 
<email>pe31@dial.pipex.com</email></p></fn></author-notes>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, 
British Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The whole enterprise of biomedical science can be seen as
an attempt to refute the uncertainty of life. We will all die, but we
cannot say where, when, or how. Almost all illness makes the future
less certain and evokes fears of death. Both doctors and patients look
to science to reassert certainty. The processes of science are used to
fit a pattern of symptoms into a diagnostic category, which in turn
posits a treatment and a prognosis. Uncertainty is diminished&mdash;or is
it?</p>
<p>Much of the trial evidence on the effects of treatments on a whole
range of diseases is conflicting, and each apparent answer raises a
raft of new questions. Individual human variation makes the
extrapolation of population data to an individual patient intrinsically
and inevitably suspect. The more we recognise these limitations, the
more the confidence and authority of science are undermined. Clinicians
working with individual patients feel beleaguered by doubt and
uncertainty. Simultaneously, health policy, driven by political
imperative, pursues authority and certainty through the rhetoric of
clinical guidelines and service frameworks. Margaret Hutchinson and
Clare Seamark are trapped at the centre of this contradiction.</p>
<p>People with specialist knowledge of haemochromatosis have issued
authoritative guidance on when to start treatment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-1"></xref>
Therapeutic phlebotomy should be initiated in men with serum ferritin
concentrations of 300 &mgr;g/l or more and in women with concentrations
of 200 &mgr;g/l or more, regardless of the presence or absence of
symptoms.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-1"></xref> When MH is found to have a serum ferritin level
of over 1000 &mgr;g/l, there seems little doubt about the appropriate
course of action. And yet, not all individuals with hereditary
haemochromatosis will develop serious clinical
manifestations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-2"></xref> Furthermore, MH has no symptoms of
illness, her diabetes is thought to be unrelated to haemochromatosis,
her liver seems to be working well, and the treatment is set to
undermine her pleasure in life for more than a year.</p>
<p>Within a few months of starting her uncomfortable and debilitating
treatment, she is beginning to express doubts about the wisdom of the
decision to proceed. Her account raises questions which neither her
general practitioner nor the authors of the clinical guidance can
answer. How soon would she have become ill if she had declined
treatment? At what age will it be safe to discontinue treatment? If the
programme of treatment had been slower, with fewer venesections spread
over a longer period, would she have been any worse off? How should she
value her experience of life while she was ignorant of her iron
overload compared with her experience informed by her new knowledge?
Does the standard guidance overstate the benefit of treatment? Does
biomedical science promise more than it can deliver?</p>
<p>Further research may provide some answers, but fundamental
uncertainties will persist. We need to find ways of acknowledging the
tentative nature of clinical guidance and adapting it to the values and
aspirations of individual patients. Decision analysis offers some hope
of achieving this by incorporating the utility value the individual
patient attaches to the various likely outcomes of disease or its
treatment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-3"></xref> The technique feels cumbersome, however, and
will need to be made much more accessible to both patients and
clinicians.</p>
<p>Health is more than the absence of disease. It concerns the scope for
autonomy and the ability to make choices about the structure and
pattern of one&apos;s own life. When the capacity for self determination is
eroded, health is compromised. It is too easy for the best of
therapeutic intentions to &ldquo;blind us to our patients&apos; needs for space
and stature.&rdquo;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-4"></xref></p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B2-1"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B2-2"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B2-3"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B2-4"><citation>...</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<?mtl /hellip?></sub-article>
<sub-article><?mtl hellip?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">BMJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed">BMJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">BR MED J</journal-id>
<issn>0959-8138</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>British Medical Journal</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group>
<subject>Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group><article-title>Commentary: Early treatment is essential</article-title></title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McMullin</surname><given-names>M F</given-names></name>
<role>senior lecturer in haematologogy</role><xref ref-type="aff">
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Queen&apos;s University of Belfast,
Belfast City Hospital, Belfast BT9 7AD</aff>
<author-notes><fn><p>Correspondence to: <email>m.mcmulli@qub.ac.uk</email></p></fn>
<fn><p>&emsp; Competing interests: None declared</p></fn></author-notes>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2000, British Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Hereditary haemochromatosis is an autosomal recessive
disorder of iron metabolism resulting in excess intestinal absorption
and cellular deposition of iron. It is relatively common in people of
northern European origin. The disease was found to be associated with
the HLA-A3 allele, and over 83&percnt; of patients have now been discovered
to have a mutated HFE gene, which is located on chromosome 6. Patients
are homozygous for a single base change which substitutes tyrosine for
cysteine at position 282 (C282Y). The HFE protein and the transferrin
receptor are normally expressed in crypt enterocytes of the duodenum.
The HFE protein is thought to modulate the uptake of transferrin bound
iron from the plasma by crypt enterocytes and is part of the mechanism
whereby the crypt enterocytes sense the level of body iron stores. The
mutated HFE protein provides a paradoxical signal in crypt enterocytes,
and the differentiating enterocytes are programmed to absorb more
dietary iron when they mature into villus enterocytes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-1"></xref></p>
<p>Patients with the disorder often present with non-specific complaints
such as malaise, fatigue, arthralgia, sexual dysfunction, and abdominal
pain. The classic &ldquo;bronze diabetes&rdquo; with hepatic fibrosis and
cirrhosis, cardiomyopathy, endocrine dysfunction, and liver cancer
presents only after prolonged iron loading when the condition is
diagnosed late. A considerable proportion of patients with
<italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic> septicaemia have haemochromatosis as this
organism thrives in an environment with abundant iron.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-2"></xref></p>
<p>If the condition is diagnosed early then treatment by venesection
can restore a normal life expectancy, and most patients gain some
improvement in symptoms.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-3"></xref> Transferrin saturation (serum
iron/total iron binding capacity) is the most sensitive biochemical
marker of iron overload. A transferrin saturation of &gt;55&percnt; in men or
&gt;50&percnt; in women merits investigation for haemochromatosis. If a raised
transferrin saturation is detected ferritin concentration should be
monitored yearly and venesection initiated when it starts to rise. It
is recommended that weekly phlebotomy is carried out until the serum
ferritin concentration is 10 to 20 &mgr;g/l and then maintenance
phlebotomy continued three or four times a year to maintain the serum
ferritin at 50 &mgr;g/l. Liver biopsy should be considered when the serum
ferritin concentration is greater than 400 &mgr;g/l in men and 200 &mgr;g/l
in women to determine the amount of stainable iron and assess for
injury.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-4"></xref></p>
<p>This disease is reversible if treated at an early stage but otherwise
can result in severe organ damage. Although non-expression of disease
in homozygotes is common, particularly in women,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-5"></xref> this
patient clearly had iron overload and I find it impossible to argue for
anything other than venesection in her case. The report illustrates the
reality of subjecting patients to the recommended treatment. Perhaps a
subcutaneous port may have avoided the problems with venous access.
Further advice on adequate hydration, avoidance of excess physical
activity for 24 hours, additional dietary protein, and even
consideration of erythropoietin therapy may help with phlebotomy
induced debility.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-4"></xref></p>
<p>The issue of screening for this condition has been widely discussed.
This case demonstrates that when a case is detected early by screening,
effective treatment is available.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B3-1"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B3-2"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B3-3"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B3-4"><citation>...</citation></ref>
<ref id="B3-5"><citation>...</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<?mtl /hellip?></sub-article>
</article> 
